<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The rooting out of the Romishe supremacie Wherein is declared, that the authoritie which the Pope of Rome doth challenge to him selfe ouer all Christian bishops and churches, is vnlawfully vsurped: contrarie to the expresse word and institution of our sauiour Iesu Christ: who did giue equall power and authoritie to all the apostles, bishops, and ministers of his Church, whereof he is the true corner stone, and only heade. Set foorth by William Chauncie Esq.</title>
            <author>Chauncie, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1580</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 165 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 73 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18573</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5103</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107788</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843483</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843483</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8222</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18573)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8222)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 315:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The rooting out of the Romishe supremacie Wherein is declared, that the authoritie which the Pope of Rome doth challenge to him selfe ouer all Christian bishops and churches, is vnlawfully vsurped: contrarie to the expresse word and institution of our sauiour Iesu Christ: who did giue equall power and authoritie to all the apostles, bishops, and ministers of his Church, whereof he is the true corner stone, and only heade. Set foorth by William Chauncie Esq.</title>
                  <author>Chauncie, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>141, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by H. Middleton, for Iohn Perin,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>At London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>An. 1580.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Popes --  Primacy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8222:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8222:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The rooting out of the Romiſhe Supremacie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein is declared, <hi>that the authoritie which</hi> the Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> doth cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge to him ſelfe ouer all Chriſtian Biſhops and Churches, is vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully vſurped: contrarie to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe word and inſtitution of our Sauiour Ieſu Chriſt: who did giue equall power and authoritie to all the Apoſtles, Biſhops, and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of his Church, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he is the true corner ſtone, and only heade.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Set foorth by <hi>William Chauncie</hi> Eſq. <hi>AT LONDON, Printed by H. Middleton, for Iohn Perin.</hi> AN. <hi>1580.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:8222:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8222:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT Honourable, and his ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular good Lord, the Lorde Robert <hi>Dudley, Earle of Leycester, Baron of</hi> Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bigh Knight of the moſt Honourable or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Garter, and of Saint Michell, Maſter of the Queenes Maieſties horſes, and one of the Lordes of her highnes moſte honourable Priuie Councell. <hi>William Chauncy</hi> Eſquier, wiſheth proſperous continuance of health, long life, and honour, with increaſe of the grace, and all bleſſings of Almightie God.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is very well knowen, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry woorthy to bee conſidered, how the tranſgreſſion and brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the commandement of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie God by our firſt parent Adam, in Paradiſe, did ſo vehemently diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſe the Lord through diſobedience, and ſo greatly infect al mankinde with ſinne, that A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam loſt thereby, not only his Angelical eſtate of innocencie, but alſo the moſt bleſſed ioyes of paradiſe, from the which he was driuen out in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this worldly vale of miſerie, therein to get &amp; eate his foode with the ſweate of his face,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.19.</note> as
<pb facs="tcp:8222:3"/> God did him commaund. Whereof it came to paſſe, that his two firſt naturally begotte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſonnes of Eua his wife, the Elder named Caine, &amp; the younger Abel, being the two firſt brethren in this world, who therfore ſhould moſt ſingularly and intirely haue loued ech the other aboue al other creatures: yet the infection of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Adams ſinne wrought ſo, that becauſe Abels oblation to God dutifully made, was of him well accepted and Cains oblation was not regarded, Caine therfore did ſo much hate &amp; enuie his brother Abel, that when they were in the fielde,<note place="margin">Gen. 4.8.</note> he maliciouſly fell vpon and did wilfully murther him, of whom he neuer was offended. This malice and ſinful enuie of Cain, hath euer ſith that time ſo cleaued to mans nature and infected all mankind, that no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent worke or deede can be lightly done by any man, but ſome other ſtraightways are rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die through enuie to deſpiſe it, and ſpeake re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prochfully of it. Yea, not ſo much as the ſingular and famous learned in diuinitie, or in any other knowledge of commendable artes, can ſet his penne to the booke for the deuiſing or ſetting forth of any worke to the aduancement of the glorie of God, and benefite of his Churche, but ſome there are, who moued with malice &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:8222:3"/> enuie, by writing or ſpeaking will hinder &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praue it to the vttermost of their powers, as by plaine experience in all Christian kingdomes hath beene, and is ſhewed, dayly, too mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly, to the whole worlde. How greatly then, right honorable, ought I, beeing not brought vp in any <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niuerſitie, nor instructed in the artes of Logike and Philoſophie, be abaſshed to take vpon me to ſet downe in writing this my ſimple collection out of the Scriptures, and other lawes, and histories: to be thereby made by ſome others a mocke and a gaſing ſtocke to euil dispoſed perſons? Wherefore, had not your honour ſo earneſtly required to haue a copie of it, whereof my promiſe beeing past I might not denie it: otherwiſe truely it ſhould neuer haue gone further, but haue ſtill remained in my owne handes, for the onely putting of my ſelfe in memorie of the thinges therein gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, as it may appeare by the ſimple doing of it. But to preſent it to you, this alſo made me the bolder, that I know your Lordſhip is of ſo No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a nature, &amp; courteous conditions: that you wil be a patrone and defender of it against all malicious and enuious perſons, which here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after ſhall endeuour them ſelues by worde or writing to defame and ſlaunder it. I pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it therefore vnto your Honour, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb facs="tcp:8222:4"/> to my promiſe: committing it wholy to your honourable protection, as vnto one moste worthy of it, for your true fauoring of Gods ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly word, for ſetting forth of his glorie, for main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teyning the doctrine of his onely ſonne our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Ieſus Chriſt, &amp; the ſuppreſſing of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh vaine and ſuperſtitious traditions and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes. The which your godly vertues are ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned together with ſingular affabilitie, iustice. clemencie: ſpecially in forgiuing of iniuries. Which appeareth by that you haue not ſought or wrought reuengement, or hinderance of any body for any wrongs don, either to your own per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, or to your noble progenitors, at any time ſith you haue ben in great authority vnder our prince, and right able to haue reuenged them: but gently &amp; quietly haue borne al ſuch things with great mildenes, and without opprobrious rebukes and rehearſals of them, made to any perſon, as farre as euer I could heare of, or learne. Wherein your great modestie, and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimitie, hath ſo much redounded to your im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall fame and honour, that I may right wel therefore compare you with the right noble Germanicus Caeſar, Lieutenant vnto the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour Tiberius ouer all Italie. Who during the time of his Lieuetenantſhip, did behaue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſo gently and vprightly to all men, that he
<pb facs="tcp:8222:4"/> ſeldome entered into the Citie of Rome with out great peril &amp; danger of his life, by reaſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the throng &amp; preſſe of the multitude of people, which gathered about him, for verie loue and deſire they had to ſee, and welcome him to the Citie. Theſe excellent giftes and qualities of that noble man Germanicus Caeſar, I ſay, can no more ſtaine or blemiſh your moſt noble ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues before touched: then the burning candle is able to dimme or darken the cleare bright ſhining ſonne, at the noone day: whereof I my ſelfe (in the time of my great aduerſities, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough moſt iniurious vexations and troubles of ſome enuious perſons) haue felt and tasted, to my great comfort and reliefe, as I can not but remember as long as I liue. For the which I can but pray, as I doe heartily, to almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie God, and wiſhe vnto your honour the ſame bleſſing, that he promiſeth to the iuſt and righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous man, by his holie prophet Dauid:<note place="margin">Pſal. 91.16.</note> 
               <hi>Longi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudine dierum replebo eum, &amp; oſtendam illi ſalutare meum:</hi> Which bleſſing of long life &amp; aſſurance of ſaluation from almightie God, how heartily I wiſh vnto your honour, I haue giuen teſtimonie by preſenting vnto you this my little worke, ſet forth for the vtter rooting out of the vſurped Romiſh Supremacie out of all the Church of Chriſte, chiefely out of this
<pb facs="tcp:8222:5"/> Church of England: and alſo for the declaring of the moſt true perfect equal authority, giuen by our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, to al his Apoſtles, his Biſhops, and godly ministers of his word &amp; ſacraments, within his true Church, wherof he is the only head &amp; chiefe corner ſtone. Which thinges I my ſelfe haue bene ignorant of, vntil it hath now within theſe three yeares pleaſed God to giue me his grace to read his holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and other good authours, and Doctours of his Church, to my great comfort and conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation. Whereby I was ſtirred vppe to gather, in this little treatiſe, theſe thinges which moued me to ſee and know the trueth: that if it were Gods will they might doe ſome good to the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of others alſo, to the only glorie of his ſonne our Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Christ, who haue your honour alwayes in his gratious protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>May. 1580.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your good Lordſhips moſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble at Commaundement</hi> William Chauncy.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:8222:5"/>
            <head>To the Chriſtian Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He moſte excellent thing that Almightie God hath giuen to mankinde, is the knowledge of the trueth, the treaſure of his wiſdom, expreſſed in his holy ſcriptures. For with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it we can neither know God, nor Ieſus Chriſt his ſonne our Sauiour and Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, who ſaith of him ſelfe, <hi>Ego ſum via,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iohn. 14.</note> 
               <hi>ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas, &amp; Vita. I am the way, the trueth, and the life:</hi> and no man commeth to my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther but by me: and he that knoweth me, knoweth alſo my father. But the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of this truth, which lightneth our mindes with the faith of God, and of his ſonne Ieſus Chriſt, by his holy word, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered in the Scriptures, hath bene many hundred yeres couered and hidden, from the moſt part of all temporall men, as they are called: yea from mightie Emperours, Kings, Princes, and Magiſtrates of this world, through the craftie practiſes of the Biſhoppes of Rome. Who to extoll
<pb facs="tcp:8222:6"/> themſelues and their Cleargie, aboue all Emperours and princes, haue by wicked pollicie, hidden and withdrawen from them, and from all Chriſtians, the ſacred Scriptures conteined in the old and in the newe Teſtamentes, that thereby the dete<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable pride of the Biſhops of Rome and their Cleargie, might not be knowen to men, leaſt they ſhould perceiue how farre they did varie fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the example of Chriſt, and the humble godly liues of his Apoſtles and diſciples, of Biſhops and miniſters, for the ſpace of vj. hundred yeares after the church was planted by our ſauiour Chriſt. So that it came to paſſe, that the Biſhops of Rome raged and raigned like Gods vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the earth, and no temporal prince durſt as much as looke vpon the worde of God, nor haue any bookes of the holie ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, leaſt they ſhould haue bene excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municated for heretikes.</p>
            <p>An vngodly pollicie, deuiſed of them, to the intent, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> their deueliſh pride &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tollerable ambition might not be reformed by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine of Chriſt: which is moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to their vſurped authoritie &amp; ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie, which they haue chalenged and v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, ſith the time y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the Emperour Phocas,
<pb facs="tcp:8222:6"/> more then ſixe hundred yeres after Chriſt, did grant vnto Boniface the third of that name, the title and authoritie of vniuerſal Biſhop ouer all other Biſhoppes: a thing moſt contrarie to our Sauiour Chriſtes inſtitution and commandements. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, gentle Reader, to the intent, that good Chriſtian people ſhould be no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger abuſed &amp; deceiued, through the crafty practiſes of the Biſhop of Romes decrees and counterfet gloſes, whereby he hath v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped his moſt vniuſt authoritie and title of ſupremacy, with which he hath almoſt blinded all Chriſtian people &amp; kingdoms: I haue in this treatiſe briefely declared the truth of our Sauiour Chriſts two co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, giuen ioyntly to all his Apoſtles, in ſuche manner, that they ſhould be in like autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and power, not one aboue the other in any degree. I haue alſo ſhewed how earneſtly and ſtraightly Chriſte did forbid all ſuperioritie and dominion to be amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which I haue approued both by the holie Scriptures, and by Godly aunci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent writers. I haue noted farther, what ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count was made of the Biſhop of Rome in the foure firſt generall Councels, euen the ſame which was made of other Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops
<pb facs="tcp:8222:7"/> of the chiefe Sees, in Aegypt, in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia, in Greece and other prouinces. I haue declared, when this vſurped ſupremacie did firſt begin, and by whome: moreouer how greatly the Biſhops of Rome did fall from true Godlineſſe, from the faith of Chriſte, after they had obtained of the Emperours, that proude vngodly title of vniuerſall Biſhoppe. Wherein I haue touched the wicked behauiour of a fewe of them, to giue as it were a taſte of the fruites of their ſupremacie. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, I haue opened the dealinges of good princes againſte their wickedneſſe and tyrannie, in our owne countrie: making thereby manifeſt, that King Henrie the eight, was not the firſt king of this realme, who did expell that vſurped authoritie: but y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> almoſt ful two hundreth yeares be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore King Henrie the eight, it was ſpur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at, and diuers lawes and ſtatutes were made by diuers Kinges of this Realme a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it. So that by reading ouer of this little worke, they y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> deſire to ſee the truth of this matter, ſhal wander, I truſt, no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger in the doubtes of darkeneſſe, for lacke of knowledge of the trueth, whiche is reuealed to vs by the worde of God, that
<pb facs="tcp:8222:7"/> CHRISTE our Sauiour teacheth vs, euen hee who doeth ſay,<note place="margin">Ioh. 8.12.</note> 
               <hi>Ego ſum lux mundi, I am the light of the werlde.</hi> Doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe he that walketh in this light ſhall knowe the trueth, and ſhall not wander in darkeneſſe of any Popiſh traditions and ſuperſtitions, which is the moſt daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous and deadly kinde of darkeneſſe.</p>
            <p>Now, it is ſaide of Chriſte.<note place="margin">Ioh. 12.35.</note> 
               <hi>Qui ambu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat in tenebris, neſcit quò vadit: He that wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in darkeneſſe knoweth not whether hee goeth.</hi> Let vs therefore heare our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Ieſus Chriſte. <hi>Ambulate dum lucem habetis, ne vos tenebrae comprehendant. Whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt ye haue the light of Gods worde, walke in it, least the darkeneſſe come vpon you, and you returne againe vnto it,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Pet. 2.22 Pro. 26.11.</note> 
               <hi>ut canis ad vomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum &amp; ſus ad volutabrum. As a dogge to his vomit, as a ſow to her wallowing in the filthie mire of Popiſhe ſuperſtitions.</hi> To the which entent, my truſt is in God that this little booke ſhall ſomewhat helpe you forward by ſatiſfying the conſciences of good people, who will reade it with deſire to learne the trueth. GOD graunt that we may all both learne it and followe it: that we neuer flie from it vnto errours of
<pb facs="tcp:8222:8"/> vaine deuiſes of men, but onely put our whole hope, our confidence, and truſt, in the death and paſſion of our ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt, and leade a holie life according to his worde, to the glorie of God, to whome be all honour, Dominion, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:8222:8"/>
            <head>¶ The rooting out of the Romiſhe ſupremacie: wherein is <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, that the authoritie which the Pope</hi> of Rome doeth challenge to himſelfe, <hi>o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer all Christian Biſhops and Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,</hi> is vnlawfully <hi>vſurped.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. 1.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>That in controuerſies of religion, the truth muſt be tried by the holy Scriptures. That by the Scriptures no apoſtle, nor Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop hath a ſupremacie ouer others.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N al maner of doubts &amp; controuerſies, which may ariſe in our Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian religion, the tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth therof muſt be tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the touche of Gods word, as well in matters that concerne godly inſtruction, as in thoſe thinges, which doe belong to a Chriſtian conuerſation.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
                  </label> And firſt there muſt be brought in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing into the Church of God, but that which God commaundeth. Moſes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:8222:9"/> in giuing of lawes to the Iſraelites, <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
                  </label> diuerſe &amp; ſundrie times hath this ſaying. <hi>Dominus locutus est.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exo. 20.1.</note> 
                  <hi>The Lord ſpake theſe wordes.</hi> And in the dayes of Ahas, when the ſeruice of God was polluted, and they ſacrificed their ſonnes &amp; daughters vnto diuels, by cauſing them to paſſe through y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fire,<note place="margin">8. Iſay. 20.</note> the Prophet willeth them to repaire to the law &amp; to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> teſtimony, if they ſpeake not according to this word, it is becauſe there is no light in them. And therefore the fearce wrath of the Lorde was pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vpon Nadab and Abihu,<note place="margin">Leui. 10.1</note> ſonnes vnto Aaron the high Prieſt, becauſe contrary to the lawe of God, they offered ſtrange fire: And this was the cauſe that Vzzah was ſtroken &amp; ſlayne, becauſe contrary to Gods commandement he would haue ſtayed vp the Arke of the Lord. And albeit the man had a good intention, &amp; an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt meaning: yet the ſpirite of God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proueth the fact, and ſaith, God ſmot him in the place for his Fault,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 6.7.</note> &amp; there he died by the Arke of God. And in the new Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament our Sauiour doth acknowledge that the doctrine was not his, but his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and ſpeaking of the ſpirit, he ſaith, that it ſhall call vnto minde thoſe things
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:8222:9"/> which he hath ſpoken: and the Apoſtle did deliuer nothing elſe vnto the Corrinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, but that which he had receiued of the Lorde Ieſus. And therefore Chriſt in the Goſpell ſaith,<note place="margin">Iohn. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>My ſheepe heare my voyce and as for a ſtranger they will not heare.</hi> And this therefore moued the men of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea to proue Pauls preaching by the writinges of the law, and the Prophets:<note place="margin">Act. 17.11</note> and this moued Paul to denunce an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſe againſt thoſe which went about to preach an other Goſpell, yea if it were himſelfe, or an Angel from heauen.<note place="margin">Gal. 1.8.</note> And therfore Auguſtine hath this worthy ſai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: <hi>Audi, dicit Dominus,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Epiſt. 48.</note> 
                  <hi>non dicit Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, aut Rogatus, aut <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ince<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tius, aut Hilarius, aut Ambroſius, aut Augustinus, ſed dicit do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus. <hi>Heare, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord ſaith it, not Donatus ſaith it, or Rogatus, or Vincentius, or Hila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, or Ambroſe, or Auguſtine, but y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Lord affirmeth &amp; aduoucheth.</hi>
                  </hi> And the ſame in an other place,<note place="margin">Aug. de nuptiis &amp; concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centia. lib. 2. cap. 33.</note> 
                  <hi>Ista controuerſia iudice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, iudicet ergo Christus, &amp; cui rei mors eius profecerit, ipſe dicat. <hi>This co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſie ſeketh a iudge, let Chriſt then iudge, and let him tell what thing his death hath profited.</hi>
                  </hi> And this did that good &amp; moſt Chriſtian Conſtantine in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> councel of Nice, for the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:8222:10"/> appeaſing of Sectes which were crept in to the Church, referred the Biſhoppes &amp; the councel to the ſcriptures of God.<note place="margin">Trip. lib. 2. cap. 5.</note> But heretikes cannot away with the word of God, as it may appeare in the Phariſees, which did greatly regarde the doctrines of men,<note place="margin">Mat. 15.</note> contemning &amp; deſpiſing the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements of almighty God. In Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanus,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.3.</note> who being delighted in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> doctrine of Deuils forbidding meates &amp; mariage, did leaue the word, and did flee to reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations: in madde Manicheus, who for the eſtabliſhing of his errours did ſhroud him ſelfe in the harbour of his helliſh in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s:<note place="margin">Chriſoſt. de ſancto &amp; adoran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do ſpiritu</note> in Adimantus his diſciple, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with the poyſon of his maſter, who did bend him ſelfe fully and wholy to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>praiſe the ſcriptures of God:<note place="margin">Aug. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra Adi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mantum. cap. 3.</note> but moſte manifeſtly in the papiſtes, which for the maintenaunce of their moſt vile and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable ſuperſtition haue called the worde of God a noſe of waxe, or a ſhipp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans hooſe, as of late did that fleſhly &amp; carnall Cardinall Cuſanus, or a blacke or an inckie goſpell, as did of late time Eckius &amp; Pighius, two princiall pillers of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> popiſh Sinagogue or <hi>Semen Turcicu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>a turkiſh ſeede,</hi>
                  </hi> whereas it is the ſeede
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:8222:10"/> of the immortall and euerliuing God,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.23</note> as ſome time did that peſtilent prelate, I meane poyſoned Poole. Therefore lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing theſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in their errours, let vs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that are the Children of God, if there be any errour in doctrine to referre our ſelues to the written word of God.</p>
               <p>And as in doctrine,<note place="margin">Conuerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> ſo in like manner for the ordering of our conuerſation, and for the amendement of our leude liues. And therefore by Moſes,<note place="margin">Deu. 12.8. Num. 15.39.40.</note> almightie God ſaith. Let not euery one doe that which is right in his owne eyes, but that which I commaund, you ſhall obſerue. Yea god calleth the following of a mans owne fa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and the ſeeking for to accompliſh the deſire of his owne heart, whoring. And whereas the Iewes had a great opinion of their fathers doinges, being drawen thereto by a natuall affection, God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clameth them, and by his prophet he ſaith You ſhall not goe in the wayes of your fathers, I am the Lorde your GOD:<note place="margin">Ezech. 20.18.</note> walke in my preceptes.<note place="margin">Pſal. 109.</note> And therefore Dauid woulde haue a yong man to rule himſelfe, according to Gods worde, and this would the graundmother of Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie,<note place="margin">2. Tim. 1.5</note> and therefore ſhe trained him in the
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:8222:11"/> ſcriptures from his verie youth. Verily, verily the wayes of the Lord are righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and the iuſt will walke therein: but as for the vngodly which haue ſolde them ſelues vnto ſinne, do break in ſunder the cordes of Gods lawe, becauſe they hate and abhorre to be reformed. And therfore hauing committed the workes of darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, doe enuie and mallice at nothing ſo much,<note place="margin">Iohn. 3.</note> as at the light, for <hi>Qui malè agit, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit lucem. <hi>He that doth euill, hateth the light.</hi>
                  </hi> As it may appeare in the Popes of Rome, who will not haue their doinges to be called in queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as it may appeare by that ſpeach of Paul the ſecond.<note place="margin">Platina in vita Pauli ſecundi.</note> 
                  <hi>Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifex ſum, mihi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> licet pro arbitrio, &amp;c. <hi>I am Pope, I may do as I liſt.</hi>
                  </hi> And therfore this is decreed in their decretals <hi>Sacrilegij eſſet inſtar,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Diſtinct. 40. ſi Papa in gloſſa.</note> 
                  <hi>diſputare de facto Papae. <hi>It ſhould be accounted ſacriledge for any man to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Popes doing.</hi>
                  </hi> And the reſt of the popiſh cleargie are ſicke of a diſeaſe called <hi>Noli me ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gere.</hi> But cleane contrary is it in the Church of God, where the me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bers do committe themſelues fully &amp; wholy to be cenſured by the worde of God, neither going vnto the right hande, or to the left: and whereas they are called Gods
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:8222:11"/> building, are gladd to be ſquared by the rule of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture, and therfore no doubt, but peace, euen that peace which paſſeth all vnderſtanding ſhall come vnto them which ſo walke,<note place="margin">Gal. 6.16.</note> and mercy to the Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el which doth appertaine to God. And therefore both in thinges which doe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne doctrine, or haue a reſpecte vnto a godly life, let that at al times take place, which our Sauiour Chriſte hath willed vs to ſearch out the trueth of them by the Scriptures.<note place="margin">Iohn. 5.</note> For in the fifth Chapter of the Goſpell after ſaint Iohn, when hee had rebuked the Iewes, becauſe they woulde not beleeue his doctrine which he brought them from God his Father, he ſaide vnto them, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>erbum ejus non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>betis manens in vobis, quia quem miſit ille, huic vos non creditis. Scrutamini ſcripturas, quia vos putatis in ipſis vitam aeternam habe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re: &amp; illae ſunt, quae teſtimonium perhibent de me. <hi>You haue not gods word,</hi>
                  </hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>remaining in you: for you doe not beleeue him, whome the father hath ſent. Search you the ſcriptures, for in them you think to haue eternal life: and they beare wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes of me.</hi> Which wordes of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt haue enforced me the more
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:8222:12"/> boldly to ſearch out by his holy ſcriptures the biſhop of Rome his ſuſpect authority, I meane his ſupremacie and vniuerſall iuriſdiction, moſt vniuſtly clamed, and vſurped by him, for theſe eight or nine hundred years, cleane contrarie to Chriſt his word and commaundement.</p>
               <p>For it is forbidden by him, as the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the Euangeliſtes do ſhewe in the holy ſcriptures. And, as it doth appeare by ſtoryes eccleſiaſticall, the Byſhoppes of Rome haue chalenged and vſed it one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſith Boniface the thirde obtayned it of the Emperour Phocas: of whom he was proclamed vniuerſall Byſhoppe, to the ouerthrowe of true religion, in the Church of Chriſt, of vertue, godlineſſe, humilitie, and obedience amonge all the cleargie, of the imperiall eſtate, and maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie of the noble Emperours and kinges, from whome they had their firſt authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and not from our Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt. The which I will endeuour to ſhewe in this litle worke, &amp; ſpecially by the two co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſions that he gaue: the one before his death and paſſion, the other af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his reſurrection, to all his Apoſtles, in like and equall manner, that not one of
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:8222:12"/> them might thereby challenge any iote of authoritie or power ouer or aboue the other, as by the commiſſions themſelues the whole world eaſily may ſee. Nowe, as no ſubiecte can haue any higher or larger authoritie then is limited and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by plaine wordes in his commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, by his emperours or prince, whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer it be that graunteth it, and as eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one of the commiſſioners, to whom it is directed, haue that authoritie which in their commiſſion is mentioned, and no other: euen ſo in the commiſſion that our Sauiour Chriſt gaue to his Apoſtles, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie one of them ought obediently to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue their maiſters commaundemente with his authority giuen to them, and not to breake it, and goe beyonde the bondes and lemitation of it. Yea, much leſſe ſhold they dare to breake it, then any ſubiecte dare the commaundement and commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on giuen him by his Prince, a Prince of this worlde: whoſe commiſſion, no ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect will be ſo bolde to breake in any one point, becauſe he knoweth the daunger of it. As for the Biſhoppes of Rome howe they haue broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their maſter Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes commiſſion, you ſhal find by their do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:8222:13"/> moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to his two ſpecial co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions before me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned: ſpecially in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vpon the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> higher power, &amp; greter au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, then any other Biſhoppe hath, or euer had from our ſauiour Chriſt: to wit, that they are and ought to be ſoueraigne heades and rulers, not onely ouer all other biſhopes in this worlde, but alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all Emperours, Kinges, and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Which being cleane contrarie to their Maiſter Chriſtes commaundement &amp; commiſſion, thereby they haue manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted themſelues to be of thoſe very Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtes of whom the ſcriptures do make mention.<note place="margin">1 Iohn. 2.</note>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. 2.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>That the firſt commiſſion of Chriſt to his Apoſtles, when he ſent them to preach the Goſpell, did giue no authoritie to Peter aboue the reſt, but like and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall vnto them all.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE firſt meſſage and commiſſion giuen by our ſauiour Chriſte to his Apoſtles, is decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the holy Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt Saint Matthew,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:8222:13"/> in the <hi>10.</hi> Chapter of his Goſpell.<note place="margin">Matt. 10.</note> Where he ſheweth, that the twelue Apoſtles be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing called together, they had power gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen them ouer all vncleane ſpirites, that they might caſt them out, and alſo cure &amp; heale all manner ſickneſſe and diſeaſes. Whervpon hauing recited the names of Chriſtes Apoſtles, he ſaith theſe wordes, <hi>Hos duodecim miſit Ieſus, praecipiens eis &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens: in viam gentium ne abieritis: in ciuita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes Samaritanorum ne intraueritis: ſed potius ite ad oues quae perierunt domus Iſrael. Euntes autem praedicate, dicentes, appropinquauit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnum coelorum. Infirmos curate, mortuos ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citate, leproſos mundate, daemones eijcite: gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis accepiſtis, gratis date.</hi> Theſe twelue, his Apoſtles, Ieſus ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t forth, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding &amp; ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: <hi>You ſhal not go into the way of the ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiles: you ſhall not enter into the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Samarita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s: but rather go you to the loſt ſheepe of the houſe of Iſrael: and as you go, preach, ſaying, the kingdome of heauen is at hand, heale the ſicke, raiſe the dead, cleanſe the leopers, and caſt out diuels: freely you haue receiued theſe things of me, freely giue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> In this firſt meſſage and commiſſion of Chriſt, giuen to his twelue Apoſtles, you may plainely
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:8222:14"/> vnderſtande that he gaue equall and like authority vnto them al, without any pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring of any one of them before all his fellowes, he gaue the very loweſt (if any were loweſt) as greate and large power, as he gaue vnto the higheſt, no exception being made of any one, as higher in au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority then they all. So that neither Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter nor any ſuppoſed ſucceſſour of Peter can claime any ſuperiority by this ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naunce and commiſſion of our ſauiour Chriſt. And therefore if they enter into any higher authority, it muſt be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then by Chriſt, belike by that way, which Chriſt himſelf doth mention in the goſpel of Saint Iohn, where he ſayth, <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go ſum oſtium:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>qui non intrat per oſtium in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uile ouium, ſed aſcendit aliunde, ille fur eſt &amp; latro: <hi>I am the dore: he that entreth not by the dore into the Shepehouſe, but climeth vp ſome other way, he is a theefe and a robber.</hi>
                  </hi> Whereof it followeth, that if the Byſhops of Rome haue challenged ſuche authority which our ſauiour Chriſt hath not giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, but they haue obteined it otherwiſe by worldly pollicies: then they deſerue to be called by the names, that Chriſte hath appointed for them, euen
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:8222:14"/> théeues and robbers. Now this wil eaſily and clearely be proued that the Biſhop of Rome hath had no ſuch vniuerſal autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity from our ſauiour Chriſt. Then what names, what titles of dignity ought we to attribute to the Byſhops of Rome? which ſo haue abuſed Chriſtes Church, ſith the time of the good byſhop Gregory the firſt: who did vtterly withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crée of the Emperour Mauricius, by the which he would haue made Iohn the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinople, vniuerſall biſhop ouer all the byſhops of Chriſts catholike Church.<note place="margin">Gregor. e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. Lib. 4. Epiſt. 32. &amp; 38.</note> For he would not ſuffer this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crée to be receiued within his prouince of Italy but vtterly reiected it: and wrote not only to the emperour, how greatly he did offend almighty God, in admitting this new, prophane, blaſphemous name, and authoritie into the Church of Chriſt, empairing the authority which he hath giuen to the reſt of his byſhops and mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters: but alſo to Iohn the patriarke, that he by taking and vſurping that authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, did ſhewe him ſelf in pride and preſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be the very forerunner of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt. Wherby it came to paſſe that Mau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ricius the Emperour was ſo greatly
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:8222:15"/> offended with this good Gregory,<note place="margin">Platina de vitis pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificum Romano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorio pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo. Volaterra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus. Centuria. 6. fol. 872.</note> that, as Platina doth report, he exhorted the Lu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bardes to ſet vppon the city of Rome: which Agilulfus the king of Lumbardy did, beſéeging it a whole yeare: Howbeit in the end he was faine to go away with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any hurt done to the city, that was ſaued by the mighty prouidence of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. 3.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>That Chriſt in the promiſe of his ſecond commiſſion, ſaying vnto Peter. <hi>To thee will I giue the keyes of heauen,</hi> doth giue him no ſupremacie, Neither by theſe wordes, <hi>I haue prayed for thee Peter, that thy faith faile not.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">N</seg>Owe, to returne to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions of Chriſte, becauſe that betwixt the firſt, whiche was giuen before his paſſion to his Apoſtles, as I haue declared, and the ſecond which he gaue them after his death and reſurrection, Chriſt did open to them in the meane time his purpoſe and intent, both for giuing them further au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, then before he gaue them, and for
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:8222:15"/> inſtructing of them what they ſhould doe with it: he therefore demaunded of his diſciples, what men did talke of him, and whom they ſaide him to be. To whome when they aunſwered: ſome, that <hi>Thou art Iohn Baptiſt,</hi> and ſome, <hi>Elias,</hi> &amp; others, <hi>Ieremias,</hi> or <hi>one of the prophets:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matt. 16.</note> then Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus ſaid vnto them, <hi>Vos autem quem me eſſe dicitis. Reſpondens Simon Petrus, dixit: tu es Chriſtus filius Dei viui. Reſpondens autem Christus dixit ei: beatus es Simon Bar-iona, quia caro &amp; ſanguis non reuelauit tibi hoc, ſed pater meus qui eſt in coelis. Et ego dico tibi, tu es Petrus, &amp; ſuper hanc Petram aedificabo Eccleſiam meam, &amp; portae inferni non praeua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lebunt aduerſus eam. Et tibi dabo claues regni coelorum: &amp; quidcunque ligaueris ſuper ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram, erit ligatum in coelis, &amp; quidcunque ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueris ſuper terram, erit ſolutum in coelis. <hi>But whom,</hi>
                  </hi> ſaith Chriſt, <hi>do you ſay that I am.</hi> He ſaid not, Peter, who doſt thou ſay that I am: but in the plurall nomber, to all his Apoſtles, <hi>who doe you ſay that I am.</hi> Then Peter, as the mouth and ſpeaker of them al, ſaid, <hi>Thou art Chriſt the ſonne of the liuing God.</hi> To whom our ſauiour Chriſt aunſwered and ſaide: <hi>bleſſed art thou Simon the ſonne of Ionas: for fleſh
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:8222:16"/> and bloud hath not reuealed it to thee, but my father which is in heauen. And I ſay to thee. <hi>Tu es Petrus,</hi>
                  </hi> alluding to the name of Peter, for his perfect faith on the head corner ſtone, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> is to ſay, on Chriſt, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vpon Peter him ſelfe was builded, and not Chriſt vpon Peter: therefore Chriſt ſaid, <hi>Vpon this rocke or ſtone, of thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of me to be the ſonne of the liuing God, will I builde my Church, and the gates of hell ſhall not preuaile againſt it.</hi> Chriſt did not ſay, againſt thée Peter, but againſt it, that is, his true Church, buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon that faith that Peter then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed, and not vpon Peters perſon. I doe beléeue there is no man ſo ignoraunt or voide of knowledge, that will iudge our Sauiour Chriſt would build his Church vpon ſo weake and fraile a foundation, as Peter was, if we regard not his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, but his perſon: who ſhewed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe more wauering and vnſtable then any other of the twelue Apoſtles, as one that vtterly denied his Maiſter Chriſte thrée times in one day:<note place="margin">Matt. 26.</note> and alſo before that did ſpeake ſuch carnall and worldly wordes vnto him, that Chriſte was faine to anſwere him, <hi>Thou art an offence vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:8222:16"/> me:</hi> and added moreouer,<note place="margin">Matt. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Get thee be hinde me Sathan.</hi> Wherefore I do leaue it to the iudgement of euerie good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an man, whether it be more agréeable to our faith, and ſafe for the Church of God, to be founded vpon Chriſt, or vpon Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: vppon the ſonne of the liuing God, who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Peter confeſſed, or vpon a man, who vttterly denied the ſonne of the liuing God, ſaying, <hi>Non noui homine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iſtum,</hi> and that <hi>cum iuramento,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matt. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>I do not knowe this man,</hi> and bound it with an othe, as the Goſpel doth teſtifie.</p>
               <p>It is certaine that Chriſt builded his Church vpon that rocke or ſtone,<note place="margin">Iuellus in replicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one ad re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſponſum Hardingi fol. 221. 222. 246. 262.</note> which was ſure &amp; ſtedfaſt: euen vpon the faith confeſſed by Peter, and not vpon Peter. And that by the iudgement of the olde fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as Hillarie affirmeth in his ſecond booke <hi>De Trinitate. Haec est vna foelix fidei Petra, quam Petrus ore ſuo eſt confeſſus. <hi>This is the onely bleſſed rocke of faith, whiche Peter confeſſed by mouth.</hi>
                  </hi> And <hi>Chryſoſt. in Matth. Hom. 51. Super hanc petram in hac fide &amp; confeſſione aedificabo Eccleſiam. <hi>Vpon this rocke, vpon this faith and confeſſion, will I builde my Church.</hi>
                  </hi> And Saint Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine in his <hi>13.</hi> ſermon vpon Matthew
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:8222:17"/> ſaith, <hi>Non me aedificabo ſuper te, ſed aedificabo te ſuper me. <hi>I wil not builde my ſelfe of thee, but I will build thee vpon me.</hi>
                  </hi> And this was the meaning of Chriſt. For af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Peter had ſaide, <hi>Tu es Christus filius dei viui.</hi> Chriſt ſaid not, <hi>Super te Petrum, <hi>vpon thee Peter,</hi>
                  </hi> but <hi>ſuper hanc petram, <hi>vpon this rocke, or ſtable ſtone,</hi>
                  </hi> euen thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of me to be the ſonne of the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing God, I will build my Church, and the gates of hell ſhal not preuaile againſt it. He ſaide not, againſt Peter, but againſt his Church, which he builded vpon that rocke of faith that Peter helde. For Chriſtes words are,<note place="margin">Matt. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Portae inferni non praeualebunt aduerſus eam,</hi> in the feminine gender, <hi>againſt it:</hi> which muſt needes haue relation to <hi>Eccleſiam, <hi>His Church,</hi>
                  </hi> &amp; not to Peter: for then he would haue ſaid, <hi>Non preualebit aduerſus eum.</hi> Likewiſe he ſaide immediately, <hi>Tibi dabo claues regni coelorum: <hi>To thee will I giue the keyes of the kingdome of heauen.</hi>
                  </hi> Now it is plain that he gaue thoſe keies vnto his Church, and not to Peters onely perſon: though he ſaide to him, but as to his Apoſtle, the charge pertayning to al his Apoſtles, and all the miniſters of his Churche, by like
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:8222:17"/> right, <hi>Quodcunque ligaueris ſuper terram e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ligatum in coelis, &amp; quodcunque ſolueris ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per terram, erit ſolutum in coelis. <hi>Whatſoeuer thou ſhalt binde vpon the earth, it ſhall be bound in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; whatſoeuer thou ſhalt looſe vpon y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> earth, it ſhalbe looſed in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</hi>
                  </hi> For otherwiſe thoſe keyes of looſing &amp; binding had ben loſt cleane, and the au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Chriſtes church had bene ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwen for euer, if Peter onely ſhoulde haue poſſeſſed thoſe keyes, as parteining to himſelfe alone, and not to Chriſtes Church. For it followeth in the ſame chapter, how Chriſt telling his Apoſtles that he muſt go to Ieruſalem, and there ſuffer many things by the elders, ſcribes and princes of the prieſtes, and be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lains, and the third day riſe againe from death: Peter tooke him aſide and rebuked him, ſaying, <hi>Let this be farre from thee, let not this happen to thee.</hi> Wherevpon Chriſte turning him ſelfe to Peter, ſayd: <hi>vade poſt me Satana, ſcandalum es mihi: quia no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſapis ea quae dei ſunt, ſed ea qua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſunt hominum: <hi>Get thee behinde me, thou Satan, or Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell: thou art an offence vnto me: for thou doeſt not ſauour of the thinges that are of God, but the thinges that are of men.</hi>
                  </hi> So
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:8222:18"/> that whatſoeuer Chriſt ſaid to him before if the ſame had not concerned the autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of his whole church, but onely Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters perſon: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al the vertue of thoſe ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges had bene clearely quenched, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from Peter, when Chriſt called him Sathan, and bad him come behinde him. But, that the right of theſe wordes doth belong vnto the whole Church, it is eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by the wordes of Chriſte that do fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low in the eightéene Chapter, ſpoken to the Church:<note place="margin">Matt. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>Quaecunque ligaueritis in terra erunt ligata in coelo: Et quaecunque ſolueritis in terra, erunt ſoluta in coelo. <hi>What ſoeuer ye binde in earth, ſhall be bound in heauen: and whatſoeuer ye looſe in earth, ſhall be looſed in heauen.</hi>
                  </hi> Yea, to regarde the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Chriſtes wordes touching that authority of binding and looſing mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to Peter, Chriſt ſaid not, <hi>tibi do claues regni coelorum,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Matt. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>I doe giue the keyes of the kingdome of heauen to thee,</hi> but <hi>tibi dabo, <hi>I will giue to thee the keyes of the kingdome of heauen, to looſe and to binde.</hi>
                  </hi> So that Chriſtes wordes were ſpoken of the time to come, not of the time preſent: to be giuen afterward, not as giuen preſently. Whereof it doeth fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that none of the Apoſtles had autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:8222:18"/> of binding and looſing, of retaining and remitting the ſinnes of all eſtates of men, through all nations: vntill our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt had ſuffered his death, and had waſhed away our ſinnes with his bloud, and had conquered death by riſing from death. At the which time they recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the holie Ghoſt, as it ſhall appeare in the ſecond commiſſion, and had that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourmed, whiche was promiſed, when Chriſt ſaide,<note place="margin">Iohn. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>I wil giue thee the keyes of the kingdome of heauen.</hi> But in the mean ſeaſon, before that was performed: Chriſt perceiuing by his diuine preſcience and foreknowledge, that Peter ſhould denie him thriſe in one day, he ſaide vnto him: Simon,<note place="margin">Luke. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>Ecce Satanas expetiuit vos vt cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braret ſicut triticum: ego autem oraui pro te, vt non deficiat fides tua: &amp; tu aliquando con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſus confirma fratres tuos. Ipſe verò dixit ei, Domine tecum paratus ſum in carcerem &amp; in mortem ire. At ille dixit, dico tibi Petre, non cantabit hodie gallus. donec ter abneges, noſſe me. <hi>Simon,</hi>
                  </hi> ſaith the Lord to Peter: <hi>Behold Sathan hath deſired you, to ſyfte you like wheat: but I haue praied for thee, that thy faith fayle not: therefore when thou at length art conuerted, confirme &amp;
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:8222:19"/> ſtabliſh thy brethren. Then Peter ſaide vnto him, Lorde I am ready to go with thee into priſon &amp; vnto death. But Chriſt ſaide, Peter, I tell thee, the cocke ſhall not crowe this day, vntill thou haſt thrice de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied that thou knoweſt me.</hi> Whiche wordes of Chriſt were fulfilled the ſame night, as ſoone as he was brought before the high prieſt. For Peter being amongſt them that ſtoode by the fire, when he was reported of by a maide, that he was one of thoſe which were with Chriſt: he aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>I doe not knowe him.</hi> When a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine he was tolde by another man, who ſtoode by the maide, that he was of them: he anſwered, <hi>I do not know him.</hi> Anone after, the thirde time, when another man ſaid, verily this man was with him, for he is alſo a Galilean: then Peter curſed and did ſweare, as S. Matthew doth wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, that he knew not Chriſt. And imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately the cocke did crowe.<note place="margin">Matt. 26.</note> And Chriſte looked back vpon Peter, and Peter went forth, and did wéepe bitterly. This I haue recited ſo muche the more at large: becauſe there be ſome, who would proue authoritie giuen to Peter by the former wordes of Chriſt: which if they be well
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:8222:19"/> conſidered, are but a manifeſtation part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of Chriſts Godhead in that he did fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>know Peter would denie him, partely of his mercie ſhewed gratiouſly to Peter, whoſe faith he did eſtabliſh with his prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that he ſhould not diſpaire, as Iudas Iſcariot did, who after he had ſold Chriſt, went and hanged himſelfe. So, vpon this verie ſentence of Chriſt, <hi>Ego rogaui pro te Petre, vt not deficiat fides tua:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chriſoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus in Mat. Cap. 26. Hom. 83.</note> Saint Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome doth ſay, that Chriſte the more ſharpely to reproue Peters pride, (who did preſume more of him ſelfe, then any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Apoſtles) doeth ſignifie before vnto him, that his fall ſhal be worſe then the fall of the reſt, and therefore néedeth greater helpe to raiſe him vppe againe. Wherefore that he might ſée and féele his owne weakenes: Chriſte ſuffered him to fal, &amp; told him of it before it happened: yet he preſerued him w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>all, through his great care &amp; fauour, that he ſhould not fall from him, though he did denie him: wherwith he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forted him in ſaying, <hi>I haue prayed for thee Peter, that thy faith fail not.</hi> Now as ſaint Chriſoſtome doth ſhewe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſt did thus manifeſt his diuine knowledge and fauour vnto Peter, by foreſhewing
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:8222:20"/> him his fall, and promiſing that he would rayſe him: ſo likewiſe holie Beda wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting on the ſame wordes, ſaith, that he who onely knoweth what is in man,<note place="margin">Beda in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Lucae cap. 22. lib. 6.</note> both as God, did foretell in what ſorte, at what time, how often Peter ſhould denie him: and as merciful, did promiſe him the help of his defence, leaſt that any of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful either vnaduiſedly ſhould preſume of his owne ſtanding, or more vnaduiſedly ſhould diſpaire for his owne falling. Wherefore to paſſe ouer other thinges that might be ſaide, hereby it is manifeſt that the words of Chriſt ſpoken to Peter of his prayer for him, haue no force at all to proue any preeminence or ſuperioritie in Peter: but they are rather of greate force againſt him, and thoſe that chalenge to be his ſucceſſors, ſith they doe ſhewe a notable fall of Peter, by occaſion that he had too greate a confidence in himſelfe, as it is euident by Chriſtes words.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. 4.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>That the ſecond commiſſion which Chriſt gaue out to his Apoſtles, was giuen in like ſort as the firſt, not with any grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:8222:20"/> authoritie to Peter, then to any of the reſt.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſecond commiſſion whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che our ſauiour gaue to all his Apoſtles, was giuen to them after that he had ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red death vpon the croſſe for al mankinde, and hauing redéemed them with his precious bloude, was raiſed vp againe from death vnto life. This com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion is declared by the Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geliſt ſaint Mark in theſe wordes:<note place="margin">Mark. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>Nouiſſimè autem recumbentibus illis vndecim apparuit, et ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probrauit incredulitatem illorum &amp; duritiem cordis, quia his, qui viderant eum reſurrexiſſe non crediderunt. Et dixit eis: euntes in mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum vniuerſum praedicate euangelium omni creaturae: qui crediderit &amp; baptizatus fuerit, ſaluus erit: qui verò non crediderit, condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabitur. <hi>Laſt of all he appeared to the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen Apoſtles ſitting at the table: and rebu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked them for their vnbeleefe and hardnes of their heartes, becauſe they did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue them which had ſeene him, being ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen from death. And he ſayde vnto them: Go you into all the world and preach the goſpell to euery creature: He that ſhal be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:8222:21"/> and be baptiſed, ſhal be ſaued: But who ſo will not beleeue, ſhall be damned:</hi>
                  </hi> vnto which commiſſion he added further promiſes, what ſignes ſhould followe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who beléeued: to wit, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in his name they ſhould caſt out diuels, they ſhould ſpeake new languages, they ſhoulde take away ſerpentes, yea, if they did drinke poyſon, it ſhould not hurt them, they ſhoulde lay their hands vpon diſeaſed perſons, &amp; they ſhould recouer. The meaning and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of this commiſſion that Chriſte did giue them, is declared farther by the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſt ſaint Iohn, in that he doth ſay: <hi>Cùm ergo ſerò eſſet die illo,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 20.</note> 
                  <hi>vna ſabbatorum, &amp; fores eſſent clauſae, vbi erant diſcipuli con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregati propter metum Iudaeorum: venit Ieſus &amp; ſtetit in medio, &amp; dixt eis, pax vobis. Et cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haec dixiſſet, oſtendit eis manus &amp; latus. Gauiſi ſunt ergo diſcipuli viſo domino. Dixit ergo eis iterum, pax vobis: ſicut miſit me pater, &amp; ego mitto vos. Hoc cùm dixiſſet, inſufflauit, &amp; dixit eis: Accipite ſpiritum ſanctum: quorum remiſeritis peccata, remittuntur eis: &amp; quorum retinueritis peccata, retenta ſunt. <hi>The ſame day then at nighte, which was the firſt daye of the weeke, and when the dores were ſhut, where the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:8222:21"/> were aſſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bled for feare of the Iewes, Ieſus came &amp; ſtood in the middeſt of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſaid vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, peace be vnto you. And when he had ſayd that, he ſhewed vnto them his hands and his ſide, then were the diſciples glad, when they had ſeene the Lord. Then ſaide Ieſus againe vnto them, peace be vnto you: as my father ſent me, ſo I alſo ſend you. And when he had ſaide this, he breathed vpon them, and ſayde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: receiue you the holy ghoſt. Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuers ſinnes you ſhall forgiue, they are forgiuen them, and whoſoeuers ye retein, they are reteined.</hi>
                  </hi> By this later commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion our ſauiour Chriſt gaue to all his Apoſtles like power and equal authority, to go through the whole world, &amp; to prech the goſpell of ſaluation to all creatures, of whome he ſaid in general. <hi>He that ſhal beleeue and be baptiſed, ſhall be ſaued: he that will not beleeue ſhall be damned.</hi> He gaue them equall authority and power to remit and reteine the ſinnes of all, both Iewes and Gentiles: which by their firſt commiſſion they could not, becauſe they had not authority to preach vnto any, but to the loſt ſhéepe of the houſe of Iſrael, I ſay, this authority nowe giuen the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:8222:22"/> was giuen in equall and like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner to them all: and not to one more then to all the reſt. Wherfore vnleſſe that Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan had mightily puffed vp the biſhops of Rome, naming them ſelues Peters ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſours, whome Chriſte once called Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, and I know not in what they be his ſucceſſours, vnleſſe it be in that: it might ſéeme ſtrange that any man pretending the name and faith of a Chriſtian, ſhoulde ſo farre abuſe Chriſtes worde and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, as to claim ſuch authority, ſo far greater then his worde and commiſſion doth extend vnto. But it is a true ſaying, who is ſo blind as he that wil not ſee? Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily if the Papiſtes woulde read and ſée with an humble ſpirit, and obedient hart to the almighty God, that which is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in his worde, as I beſéeche the Lorde they may: then out of doubt they ſhoulde finde that Peter had no greater or larger authority then other the Apoſtles had. Neither did he euer chalenge ſuch autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity aboue other the Apoſtles, as the By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of Rome haue done aboue all other biſhops, vnder the falſe pretence, that they are Peters ſucceſſours, becauſe for ſooth they are Byſhops of Rome, &amp; therein (as
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:8222:22"/> they ſay) doe ſuccéede Saint Peter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. 5.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>That Peter was neuer at Rome, as farre as may be gatherd by the ſcriptures, Therefore the Popes ſupremacie may not be laide on that foundation.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>VT to touch this by the way, for ſo much as they make ſo much a do about it, by the ſcriptures they can not proue y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Peter was euer at Rome: much leſſe that he was Byſhop of Rome. But this we can proue, that he was at Ieruſalem, and in many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places, gouerning and inſtructinge the congregation of Chriſte. Yea aboue three yeares after ſaint Paules conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion:<note place="margin">Galat. 1.</note> we read that he went to Ieruſalem to ſee Peter: and hauing bene in ſundry countries, after other fouretéene yeares he went vp to Ieruſalem againe, &amp; talked with him. Peter afterward came to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioche, where ſaint Paul alſo mette with him, as his words doe witnes to the Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latians.<note place="margin">Galat. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Cùm autem veniſſet Petrus An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiochiam, in faciem ei reſtui, quia reprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilis
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:8222:23"/> erat. Prius enim quàm venirent quida<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Iacobo, cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gentibus edebat: quu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> veniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, ſubtrahebat, &amp; ſegregabat ſe &amp;c: ſed cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vidiſſem quòd non rectè ambularent ad ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euangelij, dixi Cephae cora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> omnibus: ſi tu cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iudaeus ſis, gentiliter viuis, &amp; non Iudai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cè, quomodo gentes cogis Iudaizare? <hi>There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when Peter did come to Antioche,</hi>
                  </hi> ſaith ſaint Paul, <hi>I withſtood him to his face, becauſe he was to bee rebuked. For before that ſome came from Iames, he did eate with the gentiles: when they were come, he did withdrawe him ſelfe. &amp;c. But when I ſawe that they went not the right way to the truth of the Goſpel, I ſaide to Cephas</hi> (that is Peter) <hi>before them all: if thou being a Iewe, liueſt as a gentile, and not like a Iewe: why doeſt thou cauſe the gentiles to liue after the manner of Iewes?</hi> Nowe this rebuke of Paul (for that is worth the notinge alſo) Peter did patiently beare and ſuffer at Paules handes. Whereby it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt that Peter did not claime the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh ſupremacie, neither did ſaint Paul make more accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Peter, then of other the Apoſtles, reprouing him, becauſe hée had brought the Iewes and Barnabas
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:8222:23"/> into his diſſimulation. And here (to paſſe ouer the frailty of Peter in this his great offence) it is to be conſidered, becauſe the Biſhoppes of Rome haue claimed a ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion from him, that if there ought to haue beene ſuch a ſucceſſion as they ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine of Peter, rather then of other the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, the Biſhops of Antioche then by likelihood ſhold haue claimed the right of Peters ſucceſſors, rather then the biſhops of Rome: ſith it doth not appeare in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny place of the holy ſcriptures, that euer Peter was at Rome: but at Antioche it appeareth, and in ſundrie places of Aſia, and other the Eaſt partes of the world. Howbeit, I denie not,<note place="margin">Euſeb. lib. 2. cap. 14.</note> but that ſome hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories and Chronicles doe make menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that Peter was at Rome. Which I will not ſay, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they were made to ſay ſo, corrupted by popiſh ſetters forth of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: I can not affirme it: but this I can affirme &amp; wil boldly ſay, that al, which thoſe hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories &amp; Chronicles doe writ of Peters being at Rome, is not agreable with the word of God, &amp; therefore is not of vs to be credited, ſeeing that it is contrarie to the word of truth. And herein all wiſe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> may conſider, that ſeeing Pauls iourney
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:8222:24"/> from Ieruſalem to Rome is moſt plainly ſet forth in the ſcriptures, from place to place, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iland to Iland, from cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trie, to cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try, &amp; what he did either by land or by ſea: much more if Peter had trauei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from Antioche to Rome, and that his iourney had beene of ſo great weight to our ſaluation, as the papiſtes doe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende, by grounding therevppon the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie and authoritie of the Biſhops of Rome, it is to be thought that Peters iourney ſhoulde haue bene written and ſet foorth moſt expreſſely. Yea, of all like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood it ſhould haue bene extolled more then the iourneis of famous Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours: then Xerxes iourney into Grece, with tenne hundreth thouſande men: then Alexander the greate his iourney to conquere the whole worlde: then Iulius Ceſars iourneyes in his conqueſt of Aſia, France, Spaine, England, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther nations. But if the Papiſtes fanſies be true: belike ſaint Peter did flie in the ſkies aboue the ground, and neither tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed by ſea, nor by lande. Certainely, this is euident, that the foundation of the Romiſh ſupremacie is too weake to beare ſuch weight, as they would haue it: ſéeing
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:8222:24"/> that it hath no ground in all the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, but onely in mans corrupt deuiſes, for worldly vaine glorie. As in déede it is moſt vngodly extolled, and aduaunced, by Albertus, Pighius, Eckius, Hoſius, and ſuch other Romiſh clearkes, and Popiſhe Sophiſters: who doe exalt the Biſhop of Rome to the celeſtiall hierarchies: and make a doubt whether he be a mere man or no: whether he haue not as great pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er as our Sauiour Chriſt had: with other ſuch matters grounded on his ſuprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, moſt vaine, and blaſphemous to the diſhonour of God, and our Sauiour Ieſu Chriſt, in whoſe word it hath no ground. For (to go forward with Peters being at Rome, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> foundatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of this ſupremacy S. Paul being at Rome in the time of Nero the Emperor, did write his Epiſtle to the Coloſſia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s, in the fourth Chapter wherof, ſending gréetings &amp; ſalutations from his friendes that were then at Rome with him, he ſaith to the Coloſſians.<note place="margin">Col. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Salutat vos Ariſtarchus, &amp; Marcus conſobrinus Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabae, &amp; Ieſus, qui dicitur iustus. Hi ſoli ſunt adiutores mei in regno Dei, qui mihi fuere ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latio. Salutat vos Epaphras, qui ex vobis eſt ſeruus Chriſti. Salutat vos Lucas medicus chariſſimus, &amp; Demas. <hi>Ariſtarchus doth ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:8222:25"/> you, &amp; Marcus, Barnabas ſiſters ſonne &amp; Ieſus which is called Iuſtus. Theſe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are my workfellowes to the kingdome of God, which haue bene a comfort to me. Epaphras doth ſalute you, which is one of you, the ſeruant of Chriſt. Luke the belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued phyſician, and Demas doe ſalute you alſo,</hi>
                  </hi> now if Peter had bene at Rome in the time of Nero with Paul: was not he worthie to haue bene named in theſe ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutations, as well as Ariſtarchus, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus, Ieſus, Epaphras, Luke, and Demas? would not he haue ben a fellowhelper to Paul: which ſaint Paul ſaith none were, but onely thoſe thrée, whom he nameth to them, and Peter is none of them. Yes doubtleſſe. Whereby it appeareth, he was not then at Rome. Againe he writeth af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwarde from Rome vnto Timothie. <hi>Feſtina ad me venire citò.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Tim. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>Demas enim me re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquit, diligen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> hoc ſeculum, &amp; abijt Theſſaloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam: Creſcens in Galatiam: Titus in Dalma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam. Lucas eſt mecum ſolus. Marcum aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me &amp; adduc tecum: eſt enim vtilis mihi in ministerio. Tychicum autem miſi Epheſum. <hi>Haſte thee to come to me quickly. For Demas hath forſaken me, embracing this preſent worlde, and is gone to Theſſalo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nica:
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:8222:25"/> Creſcens into Galatia: Titus to Dal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matia. Luke is only with me. Take Marke and bring him with thee: for he is profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to me in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſtery. Tichicus I haue ſent to Epheſus &amp;c.</hi>
                  </hi> Nowe if Peter had beene at Rome with Paul, when hée wrote this Epiſtle to Timothie: then he would not haue written, that there was none with him but Luke only, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore required Timothy to bringe Marke with him, then would he not haue added that which there doth follow, that at his firſt anſwering no man did aſſiſt him, but all did forſake him: which I thinke the Papiſtes will not ſay y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Peter would haue done, if he at that time had béene at Rome with Paul, which that hee was not at any time: it may be farther coniec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tured by that which is written in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond to the Galathians:<note place="margin">Galat. 2.</note> how Iames Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Iohn made an agréement with Paul and Barnabas that they ſhoulde preach vnto the Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiles, as Iames, Peter and Iohn vnto the circumciſed, which are the Iewes. And vppon this agréement they did pledge their faith, and gaue their right hande of fellowſhippe one to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Whereby it may be gathered, that
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:8222:26"/> Peter did rather frequent thoſe places where the Iewes were more diſperſed,<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. Peter. 1.</note> as Po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tus, Galatia, Cappadocia, Aſia, Bithy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, to the which he writeth alſo his firſt Epiſtle, then the landes of Gréece and Italy, with the citie of Rome, repleniſhed with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Gentiles, &amp; hauing fewer Iewes amongeſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Al which things laid toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: it will appeare to be verie likely, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Peter was neuer at Rome, neither be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time of Nero, nor in Neroes time with Paul. Which proueth the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Romiſhe Biſhops ſuprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie vppon Peters being at Rome, to bée a verie weake and fickle foundation: as all the other groundes of his ſupremacie are, with the reſt of his religion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. 6.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>That although Peter had beene at Rome, yet could he not be the foundation of the Church, which honour is proper vnto Chriſt onely. By the way, againſt the ſacrifice of the Maſſe, and the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh tranſubſtantiation.</p>
               </argument>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:8222:26"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>VT whether that ſaint Peter were at Rome or no, it makes no gret mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. It is ſufficient, that it can not be proued by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures. But if it were graunted vnto the papiſtes: it maketh nothing for the Popes ſupremacie. For ſaint Paul ſaith,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>Fundamentum aliud nemo potest ponere, praeter id quod poſitu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt, quod est Christus Ieſus. <hi>No man can lay any other foundation, then y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which is laide, which is Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
                  </hi> And ſaint Peter himſelfe ſaith in the ſeconde Chapter of his firſte epiſtle, <hi>Deponentes igitur omnem malitiam, &amp; omnem dolum, &amp; ſimulationes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; inuidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as, &amp; omnes detractiones, ſicut modò geniti infantes lac ſermonis ſine dolo concupiſcite, vt in eo creſcatis in ſalutem: ſi tamen gusta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stis quoniam dulcis est dominus. Ad quem accedentes, lapide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> viuum, ab hominibus quide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> reprobatum, a deo autem electum ac honorifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: &amp; ipſi, tanqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lapides viui, ſuperaedifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini, domus spiritualis, ſacerdotiu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſanctu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre hostias spirituales acceptabiles deo per Ieſum Chriſtum, <hi>Laying away therefore all malice, &amp; al guile, &amp; diſſemblings, &amp; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uies and all bacbitinges, as newe borne
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:8222:27"/> babes deſire the ſincere milke of Gods worde, that thereby you may growe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſaluation: if ſo be that you haue taſted that the Lorde is ſwete. Vnto whome comming, as to a liuing ſtone, diſallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of men, but choſen of God, and preti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: vppon him be ye builded, as liuing ſtones, a ſpirituall houſe, a holy Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoode, to offer vp ſpirituall ſacrifices, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable vnto God through Ieſus Chriſt.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>Out of the which wordes of S. Paul and ſaint Peter, we haue to learne two notable thinges: one, that Chriſte our ſauiour is the foundation, and the liuing ſtone, which y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> builders refuſed, but God accepted it: &amp; honoured it the other, that the faithfull muſt be laide on this foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, &amp; as liuing ſtones, be builded vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon that head and principall corner ſtone euen Ieſus Chriſt, which the more effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually to declare vnto vs, ſaint Peter tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth all the faithfull, that they, who are ſo builded, are made a ſpirituall houſe, and a holy prieſthoode, to offer ſpirituall ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices, acceptable to God through Ieſus Chriſte: ſpirituall ſacrifices, and not car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall, or tranſubſtantiated ſacrifices, as the Biſhoppe of Rome, and his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:8222:27"/> doe falſely faine themſelues to doe. For (to goe a little from my chiefe pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to ſift this horrible hereſie of popery) I coulde neuer finde in all the holy ſcip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, or any hyſtorie of the primitiue Church, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> euer this kind of tranſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated ſacrifice was ment or ſpoken of by Chriſt: but that his Church did al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes receaue and allow the ſacrament of Chriſtes body and bloode, in ſuch ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall manner, as Saint Paul declareth in the firſt Epiſtle to the Corinthians,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11</note> the eleuenth Chapter. No: in all the he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies that trobled the primitiue Church which were ouerthrown by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fower firſt general cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cels, there is not one word or queſtion moued of it: but it was conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually vſed as the myſterie and ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſtes body and bloode. In which ſort it continued in the beſt parts of Chriſtendome, in the beſt times, ſtill: vntill at the length the Biſhop of Rome, called a councell at Laterane within his owne prouince of Italie, in the which this decree was made,<note place="margin">Con. Later anno. do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini. 1215.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſti corpus &amp; ſanguis, in ſacramento altaris, ſub speciebus panis &amp; viniveraciter continentur: tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantiatis, pane in Corpus, &amp; vino in ſangui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:8222:28"/> poteſtate diuina.</hi> Theſe are the wordes of the firſte Canon of the councel holden at Rome, in Laterane vnder Pope Innocent the third, and cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the great Lateran councell, kept the yeare of our Lord <hi>.1215.</hi> Of the which Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non the wordes doe ſounde in Engliſh, <hi>That the bodie and bloud of Chriſte are verily contained in the Sacrament of the altar vnder the formes of bread and wine: the bread beeing tranſubſtantiated, that is to ſay, the ſubſtance of it turned into his bodie, and the wine into his bloud, by the power of God.</hi> This notable deuiſe of tranſubſtantiation coulde not be found out for the ſpace of twelue hundred and fourtéene yeres after Chriſt: his Apoſtles Euangeliſtes, Diſciples, Doctours, gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall councels, knew it not. They thought the wordes of the ſacrament to be ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually meant, and to be ſpoken by way of a figure: as S. Auguſtine, to cite one for many, doth ſay expreſſely, that in theſe wordes, <hi>Niſi manducaueritis carnem filij hominis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſti. de doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiana lib. 3. cap. 16.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; ſanguinem eius biberitis, non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bebitis vitam in vobis, Figura est, praecipiens paſſioni Domini eſſe communicandum, &amp; ſua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiter atque vtiliter recondendum in memoria
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:8222:28"/> quòd pro nobis caro eius crucifixa &amp; vulnera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ſit.</hi> Whereas Chriſt doth ſay, <hi>Vnleſſe you eate the fleſh of the ſonne of man, and drinke his bloud, you ſhall haue no life in you: this is a figure,</hi> ſaith S. Auguſtine, <hi>or a manner of ſpeech commanding vs to be partakers of the paſſion of Chriſt, &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably to lay vp in our mindes, that his fleſh was crucified and wounded for our ſakes.</hi> Moreouer, ſpeaking farther vpon the ſame wordes, on the ſixth Chapter of Saint Iohns Goſpell: he ſheweth what it is to eate Chriſtes fleſh and drinke his bloud. <hi>Hoc eſt ergo manducare illam eſcam,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſt. in Iohan. tract. 26.</note> 
                  <hi>&amp; illum bibere potum: in Chriſto manere, &amp; illum manentem in ſe habere. <hi>This is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to eate that meate, and drinke that drinke: to dwell in Chriſte, and to haue Chriſt dwelling in him.</hi> Ac per hoc, qui non manet in Chriſto, &amp; in quo non manet Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stus: procul dubio nec manducat ſpiritualiter carnem eius, nec bibit eius ſanguinem, licèt carnaliter &amp; viſibiliter premat dentibus ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramentum corporis &amp; ſanguinis Christi: ſed magis tantae rei ſacramentum ad iudicium ſibi manducat &amp; bibit, quia immundus praeſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit accedere ad Christi ſacramenta, quae ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis non dignè ſumpſit, niſi qui mundus est.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:8222:29"/> 
                     <hi>And therfore, ſaith Auguſtine, he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> doeth not dwel in Chriſt, &amp; in whom Chriſt do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not dwell: doubtles he neither eateth ſpiritually the fleſh of Chriſt, nor drinketh his bloud, although he do carnally and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly preſſe with his teeth the ſacrament of Chriſtes bodie and bloud: but rather he doth eate and drinke the ſacrament of ſo worthy a thing to his iudgement and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation, becauſe he doth preſume, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vncleane, to come to Chriſtes ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes, which no man can worthely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue, but he only, that is pure and cleane.</hi>
                  </hi> By Chriſtes words therefore, béeing wel weighed, as it may appeare by S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines words vpon them, it may well be gathered, that Chriſt did not meane any tranſubſtantiation, or changing the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the ſacramentall bread into his natural bodie, &amp; of the ſacramentall wine into his naturall bloud: but a myſtical &amp; ſpiritual food to the ſoule, wher of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked are not partakers, who are yet par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of the ſacramental bread &amp; wine, which do ſignifie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> body &amp; bloud of Chriſt: for our ſauiour doth ſay,<note place="margin">Iohn. 6.</note> that <hi>Whoſoeuer doth eate his fleſh, &amp; drink his bloud: hath euerlaſting life.</hi> Wherfore it cannot be, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:8222:29"/> the ſacramental bread &amp; wine ſhould be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> verie natural bodie &amp; bloud of Chriſt: for as much as the wicked, who ſhal not liue for euer, are partakers of them, I mean of the bread &amp; wine in the ſacrament, as wel as the godly. For as Paul doeth write to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Corinthians,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Brethren I wold not haue you ignorant, how al our forefathers were vnder y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> cloud, &amp; al paſſed through the ſea, &amp; were baptiſed vnto Moſes in the cloud and in the ſea: <hi>Et omnes eandem eſcam ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> manducarunt, &amp; omnes eunde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> potu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritualem biberunt: bibebant autem de ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuali conſequente eos Petrâ: Petra autem erat Chriſtus.</hi> And they did al eat the ſame ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall meate, and they did all drinke the ſame ſpirituall drinke: For they did drink of the ſpirituall rocke that followed them: and that rocke was Chriſt.</hi> Wherein we ſée, firſt, that the wicked among the Iewes, with whome God was not plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, did enioye the ſame ſacramentes of Chriſte, the cloude, the ſea, the meate, the drinke, which the godly did: yet did they not enioy y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame life by Chriſt, which the godly did: for it followeth in Saint Paul, that <hi>God was not pleaſed with many of them,</hi> Which wordes are meant of the
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:8222:30"/> wicked. Secondly, we ſée that the godly amongeſt the Iewes did eate the ſame meate, and drinke the ſame drinke, that the godly amongeſt the Corinthians did, to whome S. Paul doeth write: yea that Paul him ſelfe, &amp; the Apoſtles did. Now the Iewes did it, <hi>In ſpefuturi Chriſti, <hi>In the hope of Chriſt to come,</hi>
                  </hi> for their redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; deliuerance from their ſinnes, and from death. whereof it enſueth, that our eating &amp; drinking, <hi>in certa fiducia praeteriti Chriſti, <hi>in true beliefe that Chriſt is come,</hi>
                  </hi> and hath redéemed vs, and ſhed his blood for vs: muſt bée the partaking of a meate ſpirituall, and a ſpirituall drinke, no leſſe then that which Paul ſaith, that their fathers did eate and drinke. For he ſaith plainely. <hi>They did eate the ſame meat, and drunke the ſame drink, that flowed out of the rocke, and the rocke is Chriſt,</hi> For, as the Iewes did it in a figure of Chriſte, by faith, in whom to come they were ſaued, as Chriſt doth ſay of Abraham, <hi>Abraham deſired to ſee my day,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>he ſaw it and reioi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced:</hi> ſo are we taught to doe it, in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of Chriſt by faith, in whom being come, we are ſaued, wherevpon our ſaui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:8222:30"/> ſaid to his diſciples,<note place="margin">Luke. 22.</note> 
                  <hi>Doe this in reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of me.</hi> Which Paul declareth far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the firſt to the Corinthians,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 11</note> the eleuenth chapter, where, after that he had declared the maner of the Lords ſupper, he addeth to both the parts of it. <hi>Hoc faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te ad mei re cordationem. Quotie ſcun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> enim manducabitis panem hunc, &amp; calicem bibetis: morte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> domini annuntiabitis, donec veniat. <hi>Do this in remembrance of me,</hi>
                  </hi> ſaith Chriſte: <hi>For as often</hi> (ſaith Paul, expounding the wordes of Chriſt) <hi>as ye ſhall eat this bread and drinke of this cup: ye ſhall ſhewe the death of the Lord vntil he come.</hi> So then, if theſe thinges be well conſidered, which I haue briefly touched out of the wordes of Chriſt, declared by his holy euangeliſts and Apoſtles: the godly I truſt, ſhal eaſily perceiue, that Pope Innocent the thirde could by no autority of ſcriptures proue any tranſubſtantiation in the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t: although it were confirmed by neuer ſo greate a councel of men, aſſembled at Rome, hauing in it, as they ſay, Archby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops <hi>70.</hi> Byſhops <hi>400.</hi> Abbats <hi>12.</hi> Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors conuentual <hi>800.</hi> beſides the Orators and Ambaſſadours of Gréece, of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine Empire, of the kinges of Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:8222:31"/> France, Spaine, England, Cyprus, and other kingdomes. Many: but all to little, to take vppon them to alter and change the ordinance and inſtitution which our Sauiour Chriſt had with his owne wordes eſtabliſhed, and ſet in his church, for the ſpace of aboue twelue hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares together, before the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry was decréed, though ſome did dreame of it. But Pope Innocent was ſure to enact there what he wold, for that he had aboue the number of twelue hundred ſhauen crounes in his councel with him: ſo that neither Princes nor Orators of Princes might hinder his prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſes. The leſſe it is to be meruelled at, that the by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome would take vppon him ſo proudly to be aboue al other byſhops, yea the Emperours themſelues, and kings of this world: ſéeing that he tooke vpon him to do more then euer Chriſt did, that is, to make Chriſt our creator and redéemer of a péece of bread, whenſoeuer he liſt, and to make that euery one of his prieſts and chaplens might do the ſame alſo: as them ſelues haue a ſaying, <hi>Sacerdos est creator creatoris ſui, <hi>The prieſt doth make his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker.</hi>
                  </hi> And all by the authority of this La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teran
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:8222:31"/> Councel, not by Chriſts ſcriptures. And all for the aduancing of his worldly glory, &amp; extolling of his clergie through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all Chriſtian kingdomes, which after came to paſſe, to the taking away of the goods and liues of a great number of good true Chriſtians: who would not beleeue ſuch a new deuiſed faith of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſacrament of Chriſt, ſet forth ſo lately, ſo fondly, ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly, neuer before allowed as any point of our chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faith, for the ſpace of ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hundred yeres after Chriſt, as I haue ſhewed. For in the former ages the god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly had bene taughte, that Chriſte accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the preſence of his naturall bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye was aſcended into heauen: but by the benefites of his ſpirite, and by the fruite of his paſſion, he is alwayes preſent with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> who doe beléeue in him. Wherof he gaue them a moſt liuely mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niment, and pledge, in the bleſſed ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of his body and bloud: a moniment for vs to remember his death, &amp; a pledge to vs of euerlaſting life, with out tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſubſtantion of the breade and wine, or any alteration thereof at all, otherwiſe then of common bread and wine, to make it by the words of Chriſt the ſacramental
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:8222:32"/> bread &amp; wine, the ſignes of Chriſtes body and bloud, he being by thoſe creatures of bread &amp; wine repreſented to vs, that we may therby with the mouth of our faith (y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I may ſo ſpeak) receiue ſpiritually y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very ſelfe ſame Chriſt, god and man, that was borne of the virgin Mary, ſuffered death for our ſinnes, aſcended into heauen, and ſitteth on the right hand of God the father almighty, thence ſhall he come at the laſt day, to iudge y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> quick &amp; the dead. And this moſt heauenly maner of the ſpiritual re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing of Chriſte, is more agréeable to our chriſtian religion, then is the Romiſh dream of tranſubſtantiation, which doth as much abhorre from religion, as it doth from reaſon. And therefore not to be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered in the Church of Chriſt: but vtterly to be rooted out, for the manifolde abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, and groſſe errors, that ſpring of it. Thus much by the way againſte the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh hereſy of tranſubſtantiatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: wherof, though not ſo greatly perteining to the matter, that I haue in ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, yet I thought good to ſay ſomewhat, becauſe I do know that the Pope of Rome hath lefte this errour behind him, in the hearts of many ſimple men, whome God of his mercy
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:8222:32"/> lighte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that they may féele the knowledge and comfort of the truth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. 7.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>That Chriſtes wordes to Peter after the ſeconde commiſſion, when hee ſaide thriſe vnto him, <hi>Feede my ſheepe,</hi> proue not any ſupremacie of him aboue his brethren.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>O returne therefore to my purpoſe, to the ſupremacie of the Pope, which I haue ſhewed alreadie how little ground it hath, either on Chriſtes commiſſions, or on Peters be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at Rome, or on the foundation of the Church, which is Chriſte Ieſus: I come to that which the Papiſtes haue ſo much in their mouthes, that Chriſt when hee appeared laſt to his Apoſtles, did aſke of Peter thriſe, whether hee did loue him more, then the other Apoſtles did. <hi>Dixit Simoni Petro Ieſus:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn. 21.</note> 
                  <hi>Simon Iohannis diligis me plus his? Ait ille, etiam domine tu ſcis quia amo te. dixit ei, paſce agnos meos &amp;c. <hi>Ieſus ſaide to Simon Peter, Simon the ſonne of Iona, doeſt thou loue me more then theſe?</hi>
                  </hi> (meaning the reſt of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:8222:33"/> there preſent.) <hi>Peter aunſwered &amp; ſaid, Lord thou knoweſt y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I do loue thee. Chriſte ſaide vnto him, feede my lambes. He ſaide to him againe the ſeconde time: Simon the ſonne of Iona loueſt thou mee? Peter aunſwered, yea Lord, thou knoweſt I loue thee. Chriſte ſaide vnto him, feede my ſheepe. And when he aſked him the thirde time the ſame queſtion: Peter bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſorie he aſked him ſo often, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore anſwering him, Lorde thou knoweſt all thinges, thou knoweſt that I loue thee: Ieſus ſaid vnto him, feede my ſheepe.</hi> Vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the which words, ſo often repeated, the Biſhoppes of Rome faine would ground their authoritie, that they haue the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall cure and charge of all Chriſtes flocke: ſo much the more, becauſe Chriſt demaunded of Peter, whether he loued him more then the other did. But they muſt be giuen to vnderſtand, that Chriſte did aſke Peter that queſtion, in reſpecte that he had iuſt cauſe to loue him more then all the other: becauſe he had ſinned more grieuouſly againſt Chriſt, in deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him thriſe, and he had forgiuen him. Now reaſon doth require,<note place="margin">Luke. 7.</note> that he ſhould loue more, to whom more is forgiuen: as
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:8222:33"/> as our ſauiour doth teache. And vpon this place Saint Cyril doeth note, Who doeth adde alſo, touching the thrée demaundes made by Chriſte to Peter, whether he loued him: that as he had openly denied thrée times that he did know Chriſt: ſo he muſt open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confeſſe thrée times, that he did loue Chriſt: to the intent, that he might recouer the honour of his Apoſtleſhip, which he had forſaken as it were, by denying him.<note place="margin">Cyril in Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelium Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>han. lib. 12. Cap. 64.</note> 
                  <hi>Quia cum alijs apostola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus nomine Petrus ab ipſo Chriſto decora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus, ter in tempore paſſionis negauit: iure nunc ab eo terna dilectionis confeſſio peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, vt terna negatio aequali dilectionis nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mero compenſetur. <hi>Becauſe that Peter being aduanced with others by Chriſt to the Apoſtleſhippe, did thriſe denie him at the time of his paſſion: therfore he is iuſtly nowe required to confeſſe thriſe that he doth loue him, that his three denials may be recompenſed with equall number of loue.</hi> Ita quod verbis commiſſum fuit, verbis curatur. <hi>So the offence committed by wordes, is cured by wordes.</hi>
                  </hi> Which iudgement
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:8222:34"/> of S. Cyril is in the ſame maner con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by ſaint Auguſtine. So that this ſaying of Chriſt to Peter did not giue any further,<note place="margin">Auguſtinus in Euangel. Iohan. Tract. 123.</note> or greater authority to him, then the reſt of the Apoſtles before had. Which beſide the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Cyril and Auguſtine, might be proued farther by ſundrie other reaſons, if it were not néedeleſſe to ſpend more wordes about it. Eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, ſith that I haue already proued ſufficiently, I truſt, the equal authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie giuen by our ſauiour to all the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles. Howbeit, that it may be far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther declared, that one of them ſhould not chalenge or deſire authoritie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the other: I will ſhewe in the next Chapter, how Chriſt did forbidde them vtterly to claime or take vnto them any ſuch ſupremacie: comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them to followe his enſample of humbleneſſe, in miniſtring as ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants, one to another, and not in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterſhip or dominion one to clime a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue another.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:8222:34"/>
               <head>Chap. 8.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>That Chriſt did not giue a ſupremacie to one of them aboue another, but did expreſſely forbid them all do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion and ſuperioritie.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the Goſpel of the holy Eua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geliſt ſaint Mathew the twentie chapter, it is written, that our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our by occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious requeſt that was made vnto him, for the Zebedies,<note place="margin">Mat. 20.</note> Iames and Iohn, did call his diſciples vnto him, and ſaide vnto them: <hi>Scitis quod prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipes gentium dominantur illis: &amp; qui ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iores ſunt, potestatem exercent in eas, non ita erit inter vos: ſed quicunque voluerit inter vos maior fieri, ſit vester miniſter: &amp; qui voluerit inter vos primus eſſe, erit vester ſeruus: ſicut filius hominis non ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit miniſtrari, ſed miniſtrare. <hi>You know,</hi>
                  </hi> ſaith Chriſte, <hi>that the princes of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions haue dominion ouer them, and they that be great, exerciſe power and
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:8222:35"/> authoritie vppon them. It ſhall not be ſo among you: but whoſoeuer will be great among you, let him be your mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter: and hee that will be chiefe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong you, let him be your ſeruaunt: euen as the ſonne of man came not to be ſerued, but to ſerue others.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus our Sauiour, wee ſee, hath expreſſely forbidden his Apoſtles to haue ſuperioritie and dominion ouer their fellowſeruants. Which as it is witneſſed by the Euangeliſt Sainte Mathewe:<note place="margin">Marke. 22.</note> ſo is it alſo by the reſt of the Euangeliſtes, Saint Marke in the tenth Chapter, Saint Luke in in the two and twentie: our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our in each of them vſing his owne examples, who was in the middeſt of them, and did behaue him ſelfe as a ſeruaunt vnto them, not like a Lorde or king aboue them, that they by him might learne modeſty, to humble the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues one to an other</p>
               <p>To the which intent, in the Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt Saint Iohn, we haue a notable ſtorie of Chriſtes exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple in this point: howe he did waſhe the feete of his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:8222:35"/> and gaue them y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> like inſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion vpon it.<note place="margin">Iohn. 13.</note> 
                  <hi>Poſtqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lauit ergo pedes eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, &amp; accepit veſtimenta ſua: cùm re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cubuiſſet iterum, dixit eis: ſcitis quid fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerim vobis? vos vocatis me, Magiſter &amp; Domine, &amp; bene dicitis: ſum etenim. ſi ergo ego laui pedes veſtros, Dominus &amp; Magiſter: &amp; vos debetis alter alterius lauare pedes. Exemplum enim dedi vobis, vt quemadmodum ego feci vobis, ita &amp; vos faciatis. Ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Amen dico vobis, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt ſervus maior domino ſuo, ne<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Apoſtolus maior est eo qui miſit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>llum. Si haec ſcitis, beati eritis, ſifeceritis ea. <hi>So after that he had waſhed their feete, and had taken his clothes: whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he was ſet down againe, he ſaide vnto them: know you what I haue done vnto you? you call me, maiſter and Lord, and ye ſay well, for ſo I am. If I then your Lorde and maiſter, haue waſhed your feete: you alſo ought to waſh one an others feet. For I haue giuen you an example, that you ſhould doe, euen as I haue done vnto you. Verily, verily I ſay vnto you, the ſeruaunt is not greater then his maiſter, nor y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Ambaſſadour, grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:8222:36"/> then he that ſent him. If you know theſe thinges: happie ſhall you be, if you doe them.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus we ſée that Chriſt did giue expreſſe commaundement to all his Apoſtles, that they ſhoulde flie ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of hauing rule one ouer an other: that none of them ſhould chalenge ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perioritie &amp; dominion ouer their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren: whereto hee did giue them a moſte notable example of his owne humilitie, whch he willed them to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe, acounting them happie, if they did as hee willed them. And theſe wordes of Chriſt a man would thinke were to be heard, credited, and obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, if they were recited but by ſome one of the Euangeliſtes: but now to the intent they might the better bée obſerued and kept moſt carefully of al the Apoſtles, &amp; ſo of all the miniſters of the Church of Chriſt: the holy ghoſt hath prouided that all the fower E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uangeliſtes ſhould recite and repeate them in diuerſe wordes, and ſundrie times: all to one effect: to beate in hatred of ambition into the mindes of
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:8222:36"/> his diſciples, and keepe them at vnity in that equall authoritie which hee had giuen to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Which the auncient Doctours alſo of the Church do teach in like ſort, to the ſame intent: as Saint Cyprian ſaying of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles,<note place="margin">Cyprian de ſimplicitate praelatorum.</note> 
                  <hi>Hoc erant vtique &amp; caeteri Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoli quod fuit Petrus, Pari conſortio prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diti, &amp; honoris &amp; poteſtatis: <hi>The reſt of the Apoſtles were the ſame that Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was, all endued with like felow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhippe both of honour and power.</hi>
                  </hi> And why ſhoulde not Paul be chiefe as well as Peter? for Ambroſe vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>2.</hi> Cor. <hi>12.</hi> hath this ſaying <hi>Inter Petrum &amp; Paulum quis cui praeponatur incertum eſt. <hi>Betwene Peter and Paul, whether ought to be preferred before other, it is vncertaine.</hi>
                  </hi>
                  <note place="margin">Hieronymus in epiſtola ad Euagrium.</note> As ſaint Ierom ſaying of all Biſhoppes. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>bicunque fuerit Epiſcopus, ſiue Romae, ſiue Eugubij, ſiue Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantinopoli, ſiue Rhegij, ſiue Alexandriae, ſiue Tanis: eiuſdem eſt meriti, ejuſdem ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotij. <hi>Whereſoeuer there is a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe, at Rome, or at Eugubium, at Conſtantinople, or at Rhegium, at A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandria, or at Tanis: he is of the ſame
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:8222:37"/> worthines, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame office, and func<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the miniſterie.</hi>
                  </hi> As many others, to be ſhorte, ſpeaking againſt ſuch ambition do ſay the ſame in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, that one of them in words hath vttered:<note place="margin">Chryſoſt. in opere imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fecto in Mat. Homil. 36.</note> 
                  <hi>Quicunque deſiderat primatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in terra, inueniet confuſionem in Coelo. <hi>Whoſoeuer deſireth primacy in earth, he ſhall finde confuſion in heauen.</hi>
                  </hi> But howſoeuer the fathers haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken it: the Pope of Rome is not mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with it. What merueile, ſith the wordes of Chriſt doe not moue him? Nay verily I thinke, that if Chriſte him ſelfe ſhoulde haue come downe from heauen, and haue ſhewed him ſelfe to ſome that haue beene Biſhops of Rome within theſe certaine hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred yeares: they woulde haue vſed him, I feare me, as euill as euer the Iewes did: ſo far are they fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yelding vnto any thing that makes againſte their ambition.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. 9.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>That after Chriſtes aſcention, Peter
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:8222:37"/> did not exerciſe a ſupremacie ouer his brethren, neither did the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles yeeld any ſuch vnto him.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Haue ſhewed hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto, that Peter the Apoſtle, on whom the Popes of Rome do grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d their ſupremacie, had not by Chriſts commiſſion any greater power and authority giuen him, then had the reſt of his Apoſtles: Nay, he was forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, as were the reſt alſo, to exerciſe dominion and ſupremacie ouer o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Now I will go forwarde, and ſhewe that as Peter had no ſuche au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie committed to him of Chriſt: ſo he neuer chalenged, nor vſed any ſuch as may appéere by thoſe things which the Apoſtles did after Chriſtes aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſet down in the booke of the Acts of the Apoſtles. Wherin we do reade, that the Apoſtles and Diſciples ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered together,<note place="margin">Actes. 1.</note> firſt they did chooſe Matthias an Apoſtle, in the place of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:8222:38"/> Iudas Iſcarioth: not by ſaint Peters appointment, but by lot. Afterward the multitude of the Diſciples choſe ſeuen deacons: whom they ſet before the Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Actes. 6.</note> and they prayed, and laide their handes vpon them. When the Goſpel of Chriſt was receiued in Samaria:<note place="margin">Actes. 8.</note> the Apoſtles, who heard of it at Ieruſalem, ſent Peter and Iohn vnto hem, to inſtructe them farther, &amp; confirme them in the faith, with the giftes of the holie Ghoſt. When Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter had preached the Goſpell to the Gentiles, and was accuſed of the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, becauſe he went in to men vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſed, and did eate with them: he giueth an account of his fact vnto the brethren,<note place="margin">Actes. 11.</note> and ſo is acquited as it were of them. All the which thinges done by Peter and the Apoſtles, doe ſhewe, that Peter vſed not any ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy ouer them: but did behaue him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe as their equal rather, taking no more vpon him in elections, then they did, going whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they ſent him to preach where they thought good, content to giue to them an account of his doe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inges.
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:8222:38"/> Nowe we muſt remember it appeareth by the ſcriptures, that Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was of greater boldeneſſe, and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dacitie, then any of the twelue Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles. When Chriſt aſked of them,<note place="margin">Matth. 16.</note> who do you ſay that I am: Peter an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered for them all. When Chriſte did ſhewe vnto them, that he muſt go to Ieruſalem, &amp; there be put to death:<note place="margin">Matth. 26.</note> Peter tooke him aſide and did rebuke him for it. When there came a great company with clubbes and ſwordes in the night to take Chriſt, and carrie him to the high prieſts: Peter nothing fearing the number of the men, did ſtretche out his hand, and drawe his ſworde, and ſtroke the ſeruaunt of the highe prieſte, and cut off his eare. By whiche and many ſuche tokens ſaint Peter ſhewed himſelfe to haue ſuche ſtoutnes and courage, that we may well coniecture, if he had had any ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie and authoritie aboue the reſt of the Apoſtles, ſuch as the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes giue vnto him: his ſtomache was better, then that hee woulde haue loſt it, and neuer haue taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:8222:39"/> part of it vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him.<note place="margin">Haec ratio re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peritur in quaeſtionibus tubingenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus in titulo de primatu Romani pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificis.</note> Which maketh me to thinke, that he had no ſuprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, ſith that he did not exerciſe any part of it, as his behauiour in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Acts of the Apoſtles doth ſhew. And this, albéeit I haue proued it by other of his déedes already: yet it may be ſéene more clearely, by that which is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the <hi>15.</hi> of the Actes, where the councel is ſet forth that was helde by the Apoſtles and Diſciples at Ieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem. In the which councel, although the bookes of councels ſet forth by the Papiſtes doe report, that Peter was heade, and as it were, the Iudge, and chiefe ruler of it: yet if a man do reade the wordes of ſaint Luke in the Actes of the Apoſtles,<note place="margin">Actes. 15.</note> Peter ſhuld ſéeme ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in that councell to be one of the meaneſt, out of doubt, not the chiefeſt. For it is the common and auncient order, that wheras matter doth come in queſtion to be argued, the meaneſt vſeth to begin, and ſo as they are of greater authoritie, for age, or degrée, or knowledge, or ſuch reſpect, they doe follow orderly, vntill that the chiefeſt
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:8222:39"/> ſpeake laſt, and take vp the matter. Wherefore thoſe bookes of councels,<note place="margin">Summa con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliorum, Fr. Barth. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranzae.</note> and the abridgement of them, which doe make Peter to be head of the cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell holden at Ieruſalem, which was holden vnder him, being the firſt Pope as they fondly ſpeake of him: they doe ſay more of him, than they can proue out of the actes of the Apoſtles: out of the which they muſt proue whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer they report of this councell, or elſe they forge it. For there it is written, that when Paul and Barnabas had propoſed the matter whereof the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie was: Peter did firſt begin to declare his minde of it, after great diſputation. And when Peter had ſaide, then Barnabas and Paul ſpake their mindes alſo. When they helde their peace, Iames ended the matter, giuing his ſentence and iudgement of the controuerſie. The truth of al the which, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it may be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> more manifeſt, I will ſet downe the very wordes of Saint Luke, as they are writen in the Actes: ſo farre foorth as they pertaine to the declaring of this matter. <hi>Then
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:8222:40"/> came downe certaine from Iudea, and taught the brethren, ſaying: except ye be circumciſed after the manner of Moſes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Actes. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>ye can not be ſaued. And when there was great diſſention and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation by Paul and Barnabas a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them: they ordeined that Paul and Barnabas, and certaine other of them, ſhould go vp to Ieruſalem vnto the Apoſtles and Elders, about this queſtion. And when they were come to Ieruſalem, they were receiued of the Church, and of the Apoſtles and Elders: and they declared what things God had done by them. But, ſaid they, certaine of the ſect of the Phariſees which did beleeue, roſe vp, ſaying: that it was needful to circumciſe them, and commaund them to keepe the lawe of Moſes. Then the Apoſtles and Elders came together to look to this matter. And when there had bene great diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, Peter roſe vp, and ſaid vnto them. Ye men and brethren, ye knowe that a good while agoe, among vs, God choſe out me, that the Gentiles by my mouth ſhould heare the worde
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:8222:40"/> of the Goſpell, and beleeue. And God which knoweth the hearts, bare them witneſſe, in giuing vnto them the holy Ghoſt, euen as he did to vs: and he put no difference betweene vs and them, after that by faith he had purified their hearts. Nowe therefore why tempt ye God, to lay a yoke on the diſciples neckes, which neither our fathers nor we were able to beare? But we beleue through the grace of the Lorde Ieſus Chriſt, to be ſaued, euen as they doe. Then all the multitude kept ſilence, and heard Barnabas and Paul: which tolde what ſignes and wonders God had done among the Gentiles by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And when they helde their peace: Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes anſwered, ſaying. Men and bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, hearken vnto me. Simeon hath declared, howe God did firſt viſit the Gentiles, to take of them a people vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his name: And to this agree the words of the Prophets.</hi> Which words Iames hauing rehearſed, doth in this ſorte conclude and end the matter. <hi>Wherefore my ſentence is, that we trouble not them of the Gentiles, that
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:8222:41"/> are turned to God: but that we write vnto them, that they abſtaine them ſelues from filthineſſe of idols, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication, and that that is ſtrangled, and from bloud.</hi> Vpon this ſentence and iudgement of Iames, it ſéemed good to the Apoſtles and Elders, with the whole Church, to ſend choſen men of their owne companie to Antiochia with Paul and Barnabas: to wit, Iudas, whoſe ſyrname was Barſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bas, and Silas, which were chefe men among the brethren: and they wrote letters by them after this manner. <hi>The Apoſtles and Elders and the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, vnto the brethren which are of the Gentiles, in Antiochia, and in Syria, and in Cilicia, ſend greeting. For as much as we haue heard, that certaine which departed from vs, haue troubled you with wordes, and cumbred your mindes, ſaying, ye muſt be circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and keepe the lawe: to whom we gaue no ſuch commaundement: it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med therefore good to vs, when we were come together with one accord, to ſend choſen men vnto you, with
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:8222:41"/> our beloued Barnabas and Paul, men that haue giuen vp their liues for the name of our Lorde Ieſus Chriſt. We haue therefore ſent Iudas and Silas, which ſhall alſo tell you the ſame things by mouth. For it ſeemed good to the holy Ghoſt and to vs, to lay no more burthen vppon you, then theſe neceſſarie thinges: that is, that ye ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from things offered to idols, and bloud, and that that is ſtrangled, and from fornication: from which if ye keepe your ſelues, ye ſhall doe well. Fare ye well.</hi> This Epiſtle containing the decrée of the councel, agréeth fully with y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> which Iames before did ſpeak, when he gaue his iudgement of the matter that was in queſtion. Sauing that in the Epiſtle it is ſaid, <hi>Viſum eſt ſpiritui ſancto &amp; nobis: <hi>It ſeemed good to the holy Ghoſt, and to vs.</hi>
                  </hi> It is not ſaide, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iſum eſt ſpiritui ſancto &amp; Petro, <hi>It ſeemed good to the holy Ghoſt, and to Peter:</hi>
                  </hi> but <hi>to the holy Ghoſt and to vs,</hi> meaning the Apoſtles, the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and the brethren, the whole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of Chriſte at Ieruſalem.
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:8222:42"/> Wherfore in the councel where Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſupremacie ſhould appeare chief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, there appeareth none at all: and ſith that neither he claimed any, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the reſt did giue him any, it is to be thought he had not any. If any man thinke otherwiſe, he beléeueth not S. Peter,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 5.</note> who calleth himſelfe <hi>compreſby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terum, <hi>a companion and fellowe of the Elders of the Church,</hi>
                  </hi> and forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth them to play the Lordes ouer Gods heritage. Which ouerthroweth his Supremacie, whom the Papiſtes do call, <hi>Sanctiſſimum dominum noſtrum Papam, <hi>Our moſt holy lord the Pope.</hi>
                  </hi> God giue them grace to acknowledge with vs, him that is in déede our moſt holy Lord, our Lord and Sauiour Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. 10.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>That in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> primitiue church of Chriſte, the Biſhop of Romes ſupremacie was not acknowledged, as it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by the foure principal and firſt generall councels, which tooke or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der againſt it.</p>
               </argument>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:8222:42"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat the ſuprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of the Biſhop of Rome hath not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ground in the holy Scriptures, neyther in the com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſſions of our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Ieſus Chriſte, neyther in the practiſes of his holy Apoſtles: I hope it is manifeſt to ſuch as are deſirous to ſearch out the truth, by that which hitherto hath bene ſaide. Nowe if we goe forward from Chriſt and his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles to the ages which enſued: we ſhall eaſily perceiue, that it was not receiued of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> primitiue Church, nay, it was repreſſed, when it beganne to take roote, and ſpread abroad amongſt them. The which doth appeare by the foure principall &amp; firſt generall coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cels: wherein the Chriſtian Biſhops did aſſemble them ſelues together, to the rooting out of hereſies, and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwing of diſorders, which began to bud in the Church of Chriſte. The firſt of theſe councels,<note place="margin">Hiſtor. tripa. lib. 2.</note> was the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of Nice: at the which there were
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:8222:43"/> preſent thrée hundred and eightéene Biſhops, beſide a great number of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther learned men, called together by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good Emperour Conſtantine y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great, in the yeare of our Lorde thrée hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred twentie &amp; ſeuen, or there about, againſt the hereſie of Arrius. But to paſſe ouer other things handled in the councel, touching the authoritie of the Biſhop of Rome, this decrée was made,<note place="margin">Con. Nicen. can. 6.</note> in the ſixt Canon. <hi>Mos antiquus perduret in Aegypto, &amp; Libya, &amp; Penta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poli, vt Alexandrinus Epiſcopus horu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium habeat poteſtatem: quoniam quidem Epiſcopo Romano parilis mos eſt. Similiter autem &amp; apud Antiochiam caeteraſque prouincias, honor ſuus vnicuique ſeruetur Eccleſiae. <hi>Let the ancient cuſtomes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in Egypt, and Libya, and Penta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polis, that the Biſhop of Alexandria haue the gouernement ouer them all: For the Biſhop of Rome hath the like order. Likewiſe at Antioch, and in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prouinces, let the due preemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence and honour be reſerued vnto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Church.</hi>
                  </hi> Which wordes doe not giue any ſupremacie to the Biſhop of
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:8222:43"/> Rome aboue all other Churches: but they doe limit him the bounds of his owne iuriſdiction, no leſſe then they doe others. As it is more plainely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by Ruffinus: who writing in his ſtorie the thinges that were done at the councel of Nice, doth ſay, that it was decréed in this Canon,<note place="margin">Ruff. hiſt. ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſt. lib. 1. cap. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t apud Alexandriam &amp; in vrbe Romana vetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta conſuetudo ſeruetur: vt vel ille Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gypti, vel hic ſuburbicariarum eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum ſollicitudinem gerat: <hi>That at Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria, and the citie of Rome, the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient cuſtome be kept: that the Biſhop of the one haue care ouer Egypt, the other ouer the Churches that are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the citie of Rome.</hi>
                  </hi> And thus much of the councel of Nice, which was the firſt. The ſecond generall councel was holden at Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:<note place="margin">Hiſtor. triper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit. lib. 9.</note> where there were aſſembled a hundred and fiftie Biſhops, called to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether by the Emperour Theodoſius, about the yeare of the Lord thrée hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred foure ſcore and fiue, for the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing of the hereſie of Macedonius, In the which councel, touching the
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:8222:44"/> preeminence and authority of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops,<note place="margin">Concil. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinop. Canon. 2.</note> this decrée was made. <hi>Epiſcopi qui ſuper dioeceſin ſunt, and eccleſias quae extra terminos eorum ſunt, non accedant: neque confundant &amp; permiſceant eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as. Sed ſecundum regulas conſtitutas, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandriae quidem Epiſcopi gubernent ea ſolùm quae ſunt Aegypti: Epiſcopi orien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis, ſolius orientis curam gerant, ſeruatis honoribus primatus eccleſiae Antioche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae, qui in regulis Nicenae Synodi conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentur: ſed &amp; Aſianae dioeceſis Epiſcopi, ea quae ſunt in Aſia tantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modo gubernent: Ponti autem epiſcopi Ponticae tantùm di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oeceſis habeant curam: Thraciae verò, ipſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us tantummodo Thraciae. <hi>Biſhops that haue the charge of a dioceſſe, let them not com vnto the Churches which are without their bounds, neither let them confound or mingle the Churches. But accordinge to the Canons and orders appoynted, let the Biſhops of Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria deale with the gouernement of Aegypt onely: the Biſhops of the Eaſt only with y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Eaſt, reſeruing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> priuilege and preeminence of honor to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che of Antioche, accordinge to the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:8222:44"/> rules of the councell of Nice. In like ſort the Biſhops of dioceſſe in Aſia, let them gouerne onely Aſia: and the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops of Pontus, the dioceſſe of Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus: and the Biſhops of Thracia, the dioceſſe of Thracia.</hi>
                  </hi> Nowe as this decrée was made by them in generall, touching al Churches for the gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and rule of them, howſoeuer in places and order of dignitie they ſet one aboue another, as Rome firſte,<note place="margin">Hiſtor. triper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit. lib. 9. Cap. 13.</note> Conſtantinople next: ſo in the Epiſtle written from the moſt of them to the Biſhops of the Weſt, neither do they ſubmitte all their doinges to Dama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Biſhoppe of Rome: neither giue they greater titles vnto him, then to the reſt, but onely name him firſt: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther come they to the councel of Rome at his requeſt, whereof they giue this reaſon one among others, that they haue not the conſent of their fellowe-biſhops in their prouinces ſo to doe. Whereby it is manifeſt that at the time of this councel of Conſtantino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, the prouinces were gouerned by their owne Biſhops: the Biſhops in
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:8222:45"/> generall by their councels and aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies: neither was there any one Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch ſet ouer them, (as the Biſhop of Rome would be, who therfore clay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth this ſupremacie) though there were many patriarches appointed in that councell vnto ſundrie prouinces, as it is declared in the Tripartit ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.<note place="margin">Hiſtoria tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partit. lib. 12.</note> The third generall councell was celebrated at Epheſus, about the yere of our Lorde foure hundred thirty thrée, by the commaundement of the Emperour Theodoſius the younger, who called together two hundred Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops into that Citie, to quenche the hereſies of Neſtorius. And in this aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, by occaſion that was giuen them to ſpeake of the authoritie of certain Biſhops ouer others, through complaint made by the Biſhoppes of Cyprus againſt the Biſhop of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>och,<note place="margin">Concil. Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſin. Can. 8.</note> as vſurping ouer them: firſt, they do forbidde the Biſhop of Antioche to ordeine Biſhops in Cyprus, giuing the Biſhops of Cyprus full authority to ordeine their owne Biſhops them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues. Then do they decrée the ſame
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:8222:45"/> point in generall of all other dioceſſes and prouinces whereſoeuer: that no Biſhop doe vſurpe and take vpon him the gouernment of another prouince, whiche was not before, and from the beginning vnder him or his predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors: that if any haue done ſo, and by force haue brought a prouince in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iection to him ſelfe, he ſhall reſtore it, leaſt the Canons and orders of the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers be broken, and vnder colour of holy function in the gouernement of the Church, <hi>Potentiae tumor, <hi>The ſwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling ambition of bearing rule, of dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie,</hi>
                  </hi> doe priuily créepe in: and ſo at vnwares by little and little we loſe that libertie which our Lorde Ieſus Chriſte the redéemer of all men, hath purchaſed vnto vs with his own pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious bloud. Whiche diſcourſe at length is ſhut vp in the councell with theſe verie wordes: <hi>Placuit igitur ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctae &amp; aecumenicae Synodo, vt ſingulis pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincijs pura &amp; inuiolata, quae iam inde ab initio habent ſua iura ſeruentur: vt vnuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> metropolita, ſecundum priſcum &amp; &amp; ſolitum morem, rerum faciendarum
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:8222:46"/> aequabiliter facultatem obtineat, propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>ius firmum poſſideat. Quòd ſi quis ſuperbia contumaci definitis obuiam ierit: hunc abrogatum iri placuit toti ſanctae &amp; oecumenicae Synodo. <hi>It hath therefore ſeemed good to all this general coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell, that euerie prouince ſhould keepe wholy, without any breache or em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing at all, their auncient rightes &amp; liberties, which they haue had from the beginning: that euerie Metropolitane, according to the olde and accuſtomed manner, doe freely enioy the like and equall power of doing thinges belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging to them: and eache keepe ſurely and ſafely his owne right. If any puf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed vp with pride doe go againſt theſe determinations: it hath pleaſed all this holie and general councel, that he ſhal be depriued.</hi>
                  </hi> By the which decrée of the councel of Epheſus, it is moſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt that the Biſhop of Rome may not meddle within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> prouince of any other: whiche yet the Biſhoppes of Rome did, endeuouring ſtill to clyme vp by little and little ouer other Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, till they might ouerlooke them
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:8222:46"/> all.<note place="margin">Concil. Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thagin. 6.</note> As it doth appeare by the councel of Carthage, whereat Saint Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine was preſent, and by ſundrie o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. But this ambition was repreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, both by thoſe prouincial councels, and by the general of Epheſus, which but now I ſpake of: according to the iudgement whereof, the Biſhop of Rome ſhould be depriued, becauſe he doth meddle with the prouinces of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.<note place="margin">Euagrius lib. 2. Hiſt. Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſt. Summa con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliorum.</note> The fourth generall councell was holden of Chalcedon a Citie of Bithinia: where there met ſixe hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and thirtie biſhops, béeing called together by the Emperour Marcia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, againſt the hereſie of Eutyches.</p>
               <p>And here, although there be more great and manifeſt printes and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kens of an aſpiring minde in the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Romes deputies, whome he did ſend vnto that councell: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding the fathers of the councell did allowe no leſſer priuiledge and preeminence of honour to the Biſhop of Conſtantinople, then to the Biſhop of Rome.<note place="margin">Concilium Chalcedon. Can. 28.</note> Howbeit this decrée which I haue heard ſay, and the learned doe
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:8222:47"/> know it, is in the Gréeke copies of the councell of Chalcedon, the eight and twentieth Canon in the latine Booke called <hi>Summa conciliorum, <hi>An abridge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of councels,</hi>
                  </hi> is wholy left out: for what cauſe, a wiſe man may eaſily coniecture. Yet the Frier, who did ſet forth this abridgement of councels, ſetting forth againe the councell of Chalcedon (after the Canons of it) in an other ſorte, out of a new tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,<note place="margin">Concilium Chalced. acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one. 16.</note> as he doth ſay: doth ſhew in this ſecond copie of the councel, in the ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>téenth action, howe the Biſhop of Romes deputies, hearing of that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crée, wherein the fathers allowed the like authoritie and dignitie to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Conſtantinople, as to the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome, did whine and mutter at it. In ſo muche that one of them ſtoode foorth, and ſaide, that the Sée of Rome, the Sée apoſtolike (as he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth it) muſt not in their preſence be ſo humbled and oppreſſed. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, for all the miſlyking and grudging of the Biſhoppe of Romes deputies, who would not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:8222:47"/> vnto it: the councell did alter no word of their determination, but did conclude the point, as they before a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gréed of it. Thus I haue ſhewed that in the fower principall and firſt gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall councells, the ſupremacie of the byſhoppe of Rome, which hee doeth claime ouer all Byſhoppes, was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer allowed: nay, by thoſe councels he was reſtrayned, though not ſo ſtrait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as he deſerued, yet within his own Prouince, no leſſe then other Metropo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litanes and patriarks as they called them. Wherby it may appeare, how falſely Maſter Fecknam did auouch and affirme in the Parliament houſe, at the beginning of the raigne of our Soueraigne Lady &amp; gratious Quéene Elizabeth,<note place="margin">Anno primo Reg. Elizabe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thae.</note> when the Popes ſuprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie was entreted of, that to renounce the authoritie of the ſée of Rome, was to condemne the iudgement of theſe fower notable councels, the councell of Nice, of Conſtantinople, of Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, of Chalcedon: for aſmuch as they acknowledged, ſaide M. Fecke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam, the Biſhoppe of Rome to be
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:8222:48"/> their chiefe heades and iudges, and were obedient vnto them. The whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che his report howe notably it is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>true: the indifferent reader, I truſte, may perceiue in part by that which I haue ſaide: and ſhall perceiue a great deale better, if hee peruſe the councels them ſelues, and the ſtories eccleſiaſticall which doe entreate of them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. 11.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Howe Boniface the thirde aboue Six hundred yeares after Chriſt, did firſt gett the title of vniuerſall Biſhop, and the preeminence of ſuprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie by the graunt of Phocas a wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Emperour.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church was planted by our ſauiour Chriſt after his aſcentio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: all the Apoſtles, &amp; after the Apoſtles all Biſhops were equall. At the firſt generall councell, ſome Byſhoppes of the chiefe Cities
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:8222:48"/> did lift their heades aboue their bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren: yet were they ſtil equall amon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues. At the councels which followed, the Biſhoppes of Rome, and of Conſtantinople, Rome that had beene, Conſtantinople that was the ſeat of the Emperour, by reaſon of their princely and Emperiall Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, were counted chiefe among the reſt: Yet equall one with an other, chiefly at the councell of Chalcedon, as I haue ſhewed. But ambition ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer reſteth, till it doe clime aboue all. The Biſhoppe of Rome gotte the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie at the laſt: but the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arke of Conſtantinople was buſie firſt with it. For in the time of Mauricius the Emperour, Iohn the Patriarke of Conſtantinople did chalenge to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the title of vniuerſall Biſhoppe: calling for that purpoſe a councell of the Grecians,<note place="margin">Platina de vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis Pontific. Rom. in Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorio primo.</note> and maintayning him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in it, by the authoritie of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour: who as he willed other By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes to make that account of him, &amp; accordingly to obey him: ſo namely he required it at the handes of Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:8222:49"/> the firſt, Biſhoppe of Rome, to whom he wrote purpoſely touching this matter.<note place="margin">Gregorius lib epiſto. 4. cap. 76. &amp; lib. 6. cap. 194.</note> But Gregorie hauing receiued the Emperours letters, wrot backe again vnto him, that the name and title of vniuerſall Byſhop, which Iohn did take vppon him, is a newe, proud, vaine, fooliſhe, preſumptuous, and blaſphemous name: that whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer doth either call him ſelfe ſo, or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be called, he in this his pride is a forerunner of Antichriſt. Wherefore he maketh this humble requeſt vnto the Emperour, that hee will repreſſe this proude attempt of Iohn: who by the ſwelling puffe of vaine glorie doth lift vp his necke againſt the Lorde al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie, and the ordinaunces of the Fathers. As for my ſelfe, ſaith he, I truſt in the Lord that Iohn ſhall not bowe my necke vnto him, no not with ſwordes. Which as hee wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth boldly vnto to the Emperour: ſo doeth he write alſo to the Patriarke Iohn him ſelfe,<note place="margin">Epiſtolarum lib. 4. cap. 82.</note> exhorting him to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from the vſurping of ſo fooliſhe and arrogant a name. And what ſaith
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:8222:49"/> he, wilt thou aunſwere at the daye of iudgement to Chriſte the heade of the vniuerſall Church: who goeſt about to ſet all his members vnder thee, by this name and title of vniuerſall Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe. But in concluſion, what ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer Gregorie could ſay, either to the Emperour, or to the Patriark, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour being inflamed with wrath and anger againſt Gregorie, for refu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to yeeld to the Patriarks pride, did call his ſoldiers out of Italy who before did defende it againſt the Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bardes,<note place="margin">Platina in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Gregorii primi.</note> and exhorted the Lombardes to ſet vppon the Romanes, and to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſege the citie of Rome, which Agilul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus the king of Lombardes did: and continued his ſiege a whole yeare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the citie, putting it to great di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe. But they defended ſo well the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues againſt him and all his power: that at the laſt he was faine to raiſe his ſiege, returning home to Millan with great diſhonour, through the gratious prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of Almighty God. So Gregorie withſtoode Iohn: not ſuffering the title of vniuerſall By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppe
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:8222:50"/> to be giuen him.<note place="margin">Gregor. Epiſt. lib. 7. cap. 30.</note> Neither woulde he him ſelfe accepte it, when Eulogius the Biſhoppe of Alexandria in his leters did giue it to him, whom he requeſteth not to giue him y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> proud name and title: which he would haue to be denyed no leſſe to him then to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. But that which the figtrée, the vine, and oliue did refuſe: the bramble tooke vppon him, as it is written in the Iudges.<note place="margin">Iudg. 9.</note> That which Gregorie refuſed, and willed all god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Byſhoppes to refuſe: Boniface the thirde, the ſucceſſor of Gregorie in the ſee of Rome,<note place="margin">Platina in vita Bonifac. 3.</note> not onely tooke it, but alſo ſought it. For after that Mauricius the Emperour was tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terouſly murthered by Phocas: Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niface being puffed vp with as great pride as euer was Iohn the Patriark or greater, neuer ceaſed from making ſuite vnto Phocas, that he might bée proclaimed vniuerſall Byſhoppe, the generall Vicar of Chriſt on earth, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till he did obteine it, which was about the yeare of our Lorde ſixe hundred &amp; fiue.<note place="margin">Cent. 7. fol. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>29.</note> And this is the firſt birth
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:8222:50"/> of the Popes ſupremacie and vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall dignitie: which came not from our Sauiour Chriſt, but from the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour Phocas a traitour and murthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of his Lorde and maſter. Who, as he murthered his maiſter, the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour Mauricius, euen that Maurici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us who woulde haue giuen the ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie to Iohn the Patriarke of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople: ſo he himſelf, who gaue it to Boniface Biſhop of Rome, was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter murthered by his Leiutenantes, Heracleonas and Heraclius. A iuſt iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of God, for his gret iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geſt the which this was not y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> leaſt, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he did foſter the ambitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the Biſhoppe of Rome, promoting him to the ſupremacie: out of the which there iſſued afterwarde ſo great cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities to the Church of God.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. 12.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>How the Popes hauing gotten the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy ouer al Biſhops did clime higher and higher, vntill they had it alſo ouer Princes and Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours.</p>
               </argument>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:8222:51"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>Fter that the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome had obteined y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> title of preeminence ouer all other Biſhops and Churches by the graunt of Pho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas: the ſucceſſours of Boniface, to whom the graunt was made, were very buſie ſtil, hauing gotten an inch, to make it an ell: and get in their whole bodies, where they had gotten in their heads: I meane, to increaſe and augment the authoritie, whereof the title they had purchaſed. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they trauelled ſo painfully, and did ſpéede ſo wel, that they ſet themſelues at length in the poſſeſſion of that ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie, which they clayme at this day: whereby they did not onely ſet themſelues aboue Biſhops, but alſo by craftie meanes they crept cleane out of the Emperours iuriſdiction, and by little and little raiſed vp them ſelues aboue all the Emperours, and princes of the earth. So that in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of time, when they had growen
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:8222:51"/> from Biſhops to be Popes, they grew from Popes to be princes, nay aboue Princes: yea according to S. Paules prophecie of Antichriſt,<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2.</note> they did ſit as God in the Temple of God. For to conſider the degrées and pointes of their exaltation, and chaunge of their ſtate, how they crept from their hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militie to the throne of their ſuprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and ſettled themſelues in it: firſt wheras before they were ſubiect to the Emperours, and coulde not be made Biſhops of Rome without their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, and allowing of the election: they gott their election into their owne handes, ſo that they néeded not the Emperours conſent, yea they made Emperours, the ſtouteſt of them at the length to be ſubiect vnto them, and gladde to haue them their good Lords. Platina, their own man, in the ſtorie that he writeth of the Popes liues, is a ſufficient witnes of it: for in the life of Pelagius the ſecond, hauing ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed howe the cleargie did chooſe him Biſhop of Rome, he ſaith,<note place="margin">Platin. de viti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> pontificum Romanorum in Pelagio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> that at that time the Cleargies election of the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:8222:52"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:8222:52"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:8222:53"/> biſhop was nothing worth, vnleſſe that the Emperour had allowed his election. But this was before that Boniface had gotten the title of ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacie. Afterwarde, as the ſame Platina doeth ſhewe, though for a while the Emperour had ſtill to deale with their elections, yet they often grudged at it,<note place="margin">Platina in Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſchali. 1. Adri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an. 3. Leone 9. Gregorio. 7.</note> and ſometimes did it without him, and ſaide they ought ſo to doe, and at the laſt made a law that the Pope ſhould bee choſen by the cleargy of Rome, and the Emperours authoritie ſhould haue nothing to doe in it. Moreouer the Biſhops of Rome before that time, as all other biſhops, were ſubiecte and obedient to their Emperours and Princes. They were called to generall councels, by the writtes and commaundementes of Emperours, and they obeyed: as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſhewed of the foure principall councels ſummoned by Conſtantinus Theodoſius, and Martianus. Neither onely did they obey, when they were ſummoned to councels: but in all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thinges they did behaue them
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:8222:53"/> ſelues, as it becommeth ſubiectes to their ſouereigne Lordes.<note place="margin">Matt. 22.</note> As our ſauiour Chriſt had taught them: who both did pay tribute him ſelfe vnto Ceſar, and commanded his Diſciples to giue to Ceſar, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> whiche is Ceſars, and was obedient vnto the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours Lawes euen vnto death,<note place="margin">Matt. 26.</note> and neuer tooke vppon him to diſobey ſo much as the Emperours miniſters, or officers whatſoeuer. As they had learned of Peter: who ſaith to all the faithfull,<note place="margin">1. Pet. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Subditi estote omni humanae creaturae propter Deum: ſiue Regi, quaſi praecellenti; ſiue ducibus, tanquam ab eo miſſis, ad vindictam malorum laudem, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rò bonorum: <hi>Be you ſubiect and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to all ordinaunce of man, for the Lords ſake: whether it be vnto y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> King as vnto the ſuperiour, or vnto the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours as vnto them that are ſent of him, for the puniſhment of euil do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, and for the praiſe of them that doe well.</hi>
                  </hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 13.</note> As ſaint Paul did warne the Romanes, and in the Romanes all Chriſtians: <hi>Let euery ſoule be ſubiect vnto the higher powers, for there is
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:8222:54"/> no power but of God: and the powers that be, are ordeined of God. Who ſo euer therefore reſiſteth the power, reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth the ordinance of God, and they that reſiſt, ſhall receiue to themſelues iudgement.</hi> Theſe leſſons of Chriſte, of Peter, of Paul, the ancient biſhops of Rome did ſhewe by their example, they thought them to pertaine not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the laitie, but alſo to the cleargie not only to the pooreſt, but alſo to the richeſt Biſhops. They thought the ſame which Chryſoſtome doth write vpon Saint Paul, that obedience to Princes is commanded to all eſtates: <hi>Omnis anima poteſtatibus ſupereminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus ſit ſubdita:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chriſoſtom. in Epiſt. ad Roma. homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>etiamſi Apostolus ſis, ſi Euangelista, ſi propheta, ſiue quiſquis tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem fueris. Neque enim pietate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſubuertit iſta ſubiectio. <hi>Let euery ſoule be ſubiect to the higher powers: though thou be an Apoſtle,</hi>
                  </hi> ſaith Chriſoſtome, <hi>though an Euangeliſt, though a prophet: for godlines is not empaired by this obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and ſubiection.</hi> They thought that Conſtantine did the duetie of a godly Emperour, who when a councel
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:8222:54"/> of Biſhops aſſembled at Tyrus had wrongfully and vniuſtly condemned Athanaſius: he commanded them all to come to him ſpéedily at Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople, that you may proue, ſaith he,<note place="margin">Hiſtoria tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>partit. lib. 3. Cap. 7.</note> the ſoundneſſe and vprightnes of your ſentence and iudgement, <hi>Coram me quem proprium eſſe Dei ministrum, neque vos negabitis, <hi>Before me whome your ſelues can not denie to be the true and right ſeruant of God.</hi>
                  </hi> But after that the ſucceſſors of Boniface had felt the ſauour of the ſupremacie: neither our ſauiour Chriſtes example, nor his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles authoritie, nor the iudgement of the fathers, nor the practiſe of the godly biſhops coulde kepe the Pope within his boundes, in ſubiection to the Emperour: but he exempted firſt himſelf from his power, afterward al the cleargie, and laſtly brought the Emperour in ſubiection to him ſelf, taking the two ſwordes vpon him, the ſpirituall and the temporall.</p>
               <p>Then ceaſed the Popes to call the Emperours their Lords,<note place="margin">Greg. Epiſto. lib. 4. cap. 76. &amp; paſſim.</note> as Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorie the firſt did call them, after his
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:8222:55"/> godly predeceſſors: and they beganne to call them their ſonnes, and their children, as nowe they vſe to write vnto them. Then did they make de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees, that the ciuil magiſtrate ſhould haue nought to deale with any of the cleargie:<note place="margin">Nouell. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitut. Iuſtini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</note> where as before, Iuſtinian the Emperour did gouerne and rule the higheſt of them, as his lawes do ſhew, the which are yet extant. Then did they count them ſelues the onely Vicars of God on earth: not acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging that in Princes, which Eleu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therius did in Lucius the auncient kinge of Englande: whome he willed as Gods Vicar within his own king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to drawe him lawes out of the ſcriptures, there by to rule his owne ſubiectes. Then did they forbid, that biſhoprickes and ſpirituall liuinges ſhoulde be taken at the handes of lay me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, no not of Emperours: they made them ſelues Lords of them, and there<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore did condemne both ſuch as gaue them otherwiſe, and ſuch as receiued them. To be ſhort, they grewe to ſuch outrage of preſumption, of rebellio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:8222:55"/> of ryot, of tyrannie, of extortio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of luſt, and all enormities: that a man might knowe the trée by the fruites, and the wiſe muſt néede abhorre that ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie, out of the which ſuch villanies and abhominations did ſpringe into the worlde.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. 13.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>What fruites did ſpringe out of the ſupremacie, wherein the wicked miſchiefes and abominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the Popes liues and dealinges are, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched by their owne writers.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Heſe fruites of the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy of the Romane Byſhoppes, woulde be conſidered further in their liues and doings: which if I ſhoulde endeuor to runne them ouer all, ſuch as pertaine vnto this purpoſe: I ſhoulde neuer make an ende. Wherefore I will touch but onely certaine of the chiefeſt, as it were for a taſt: noting out of them,
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:8222:56"/> as neere as I can, the very naturall fruites of the Romiſh ſupremacie. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongeſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> which firſt there commeth in place their contention and ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in procuring of the Popedome, for the which there hath ben co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly ſuch corruption, ſuch bribery, ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate, ſuch impriſoning, murthering &amp; poyſoning, &amp; all euill meanes vſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt them: that in Platina, their owne ſecretarie and writer of their liues, it is a common note in verie many of them, that they were made Popes, ſome by Mars, ſome by monie, ſome by fauour of friendes, ſome by power of noble men, ſome by ſorcerie and magike, ſome by like pollicies of the Deuill.<note place="margin">Platina in Iohanne 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Pontifices ipſi a Petri vesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gijs diſceſſerant,</hi> ſaith Platina. <hi>The Byſhoppes of Rome were now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from Peters ſteppes.</hi> Which complainte he doth make vppon occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of their hatred, conceyued by one of them againſt another, through their ambition. For Iohn the ix. was vexed by Martine the ſeconde: ſo that being impriſoned he was faine to eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cape
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:8222:56"/> by flight: Martine the ſeconde, made Pope through euill meanes, did reſtore Formoſus, whome Iohn had depryued. Afterwarde Formoſus getting the rome by bryberie, came in by periurie vnto it, and liued in it ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly. Steuen the ſixt that ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céeded him, did abrogate and repeale al the actes of Formoſus, whoſe body he digged alſo out of his graue, cut off his two fingers, wherewith he hallo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wed Prieſtes, and caſt them into the riuer. After Steuen came Romanus, Theodorus, and Iohn the tenth, who did repeale the actes of Steuen, and reſtored Formoſus actes to full au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie againe. Which villanous dealing of them one againſt an other, enforceth Platina him ſelfe,<note place="margin">Platina in Formoſ. 1. Stephan. 6. Romano. 1. Benedicto. 4. Chriſtophero 1. &amp;c.</note> though o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe fauouring the Popes, to breake out into theſe complaintes: that the vertue and honeſtie of the Biſhops of Rome nowe was decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: that they did aſpire and attaine vnto the office by ambition and bribe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie: that hereof did ſpring their ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred one againſt an other, when they
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:8222:57"/> were put beſide it: that of this hatred there a roſe a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon cuſtome, which was almoſt kept alwayes afterward, that what the former Biſhops had done &amp; decréed, their ſucceſſors would either wholy or in part take away: that theſe petie Popes (for ſo he doeth call them) did thinke of nothinge elſe, but how they mighte deface the name and dignitie of their predeceſſors, by repealing of their actes, that when the Church did waxe wanton with honor and wealth, there being no prince in Rome to repreſſe mens wickedneſſe, the looſe licentiouſneſſe of ſinne did bring foorth theſe beaſts, who through ambition and briberie did inuade the ſée of Peter: finally, that theſe Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops had but ſhort liues, bicauſe God did quickly take them out of the earth, as it were certaine monſters. And theſe are the teſtimonies that Platina doth giue of this trimme ſucceſſion of the Romane Biſhops, following one an other, when yet their power was leſſer, and their ſupremacie not gro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wen ſo high. If I ſhould goe forward
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:8222:57"/> to ſpeake of their behauiour, who came after theſe men, and did ſuccéede them in that ſée: as namely of the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie of Sergius the third,<note place="margin">Platina in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis horum pontificum.</note> who did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head the carcaſe of Pope Formoſus, long after he was dead: of the beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe of Iohn the thirtéenth, a man euen from his youth giuen ouer to fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy luſtes, and all diſhoneſtie of life: of the ſacriledge of Boniface the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenth, who being driuen of the citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens out of Rome, did rob Saint Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Church of iewels, and making money of them, returned to buy the Popedome: of Iohn the ſixtéenth, who to enrich his kinſemen, ſpared ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther heauen nor earth, regarding ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gods honour, nor the Churches commoditie: of Silueſter the ſecond, who gaue him ſelfe vnto the diuell, that he would helpe him to be Pope, vpon condition that he ſhould haue him wholy after his death: of Benet the ninth, Silueſter the third, Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie the ſixt, of whom the firſt ſolde, the other bought the dignitie, and ſtroue together for it, thrée moſt ougly mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:8222:58"/> as Platina doth call them, and to paſſe ouer the reſt, of Alexander the vi. in our owne dayes, who waſted and ſpoyled all Italy moſt miſerably to make his baſtarde Borgia Ceſar a Prince: and hauing at the length certaine of the richeſt Cardinals at ſupper, did minde to poyſon them to haue their riches for his baſtarde,<note place="margin">Onuphrius in vita Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dri ſexti.</note> but him ſelfe was poyſoned through the errour of his butler, who miſtakinge the flagon gaue the good wine to the Cardinals, and to the Pope the poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon: If further I ſhoulde ſpeake of all their ſtraunge and horrible ſciſmes and contentions, when two or three were made Popes at one time, and raiſed their thrones at once in diuerſe places, of the which kind themſelues doe number thirtie ſciſmes, ſome of them laſting for fiftie yeares toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as namely that for which the councell of Conſtance was aſſembled by Sigiſmund the Emperour, becauſe the ſtate of Chriſtendome was trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled then with three Popes, all cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen by Cardinals. The firſte Pope in
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:8222:58"/> Italy, the ſeconde Pope in Fraunce, the thirde Pope in Spaine, and none would yéeld to other: y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very rehearſal of theſe and the like pointes, would I feare be tedious, and I coulde ſay no more of them, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that which Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tina doth ſay often, <hi>O quantum dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerarunt isti Pontifices a ſuis maioribus: <hi>Alas howe greatly do theſe Biſhoppes degenerate from their aunceſters.</hi>
                  </hi> Or rather that which the Apoſtle doth write to the Romanes, he ſpake it of the Gentiles, it was fulfilled in the Popes: <hi>Bicauſe they knewe God,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>and did not glorifie him as God, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came vaine in their owne imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and turned the glory of the incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible GOD into the ſimilitude of the image of a corruptible man: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God gaue them vp to their hearts luſtes, vnto vncleanneſſe, vnto vile af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, vnto reprobate mindes.</hi> Wherefore, to leaue the reſt which might be ſaide touching theſe fruites of the Romiſh ſupremacie, to the fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſearch and conſideration of the godly reader: onely this I can not
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:8222:59"/> chooſe, but I muſt expreſly note, as the chiefeſt pearle of their ſupremacie, that after they had gotten the loftie title of it by the graunt of Phocas, of Emperours ſubiectes, they became the Lords of Emperours, commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding what they liſt, depoſing whome they liſt, as though they were the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uereigne kings of all the earth. Firſt Conſtantine the Pope did onely reſiſt Philippicus the Emperour, refuſing to plucke downe images as he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded him. Then Gregorie the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, when Leo the Emperour gaue him the ſame charge, did take away from him his Empire in Italie: and Gregorie the third did both depriue him of the Empire, and of the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the faithfull. But in this point Gregorie the ſeuenth, who was na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Hildebrand, before he was Pope did farre paſſe all his predeceſſors: for whereas before that time the Emperour had authorite to giue by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopriks and other ſpiritual liuings, through all his dominions: Gregory the ſeuenth tooke authoritie vppon
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:8222:59"/> him to forbidde the Emperour to giue any ſuch liuinges, threatening him withall, that if he did giue them, hee woulde condemne both him, and whoſoeuer ſhold receiue them. Which commaundement of the Pope for as much as Henrie the Emperour miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſliked, thinking it vniuſt, and would not therefore obey it: Gregorie the Pope excommunicated him, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priued him of his Empyre, aſſoyling all his ſubiectes of their allegeances vnto him, and charging them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all that they ſhoulde not obey him. Wherevppon a parte of his Empire did rebell, and great warres were rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed againſt him by the Saxons: which, and other diſcommodities y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> did enſue I will not ſtande vppon. Onely I do note the preſumption of theſe Prieſts who both rebell them ſelues againſte their Lordes and Emperours and ſtir vp others to rebellion, vnder the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of their ſupremacie. Whereof we neede not to ſéeke for the proofe in Gregory y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſeuenth, who did ſo abuſe the good Emperour Henrie, we haue
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:8222:60"/> had experience of it at home within our owne realme, which Pius the fifth did raiſe to rebellion againſt our gratious Quéene Elizabeth: whome the Lorde defende for euer, as hee did then defend her: when Pope did curſe her, he did bleſſe her. But to knit vp this point of the fruites of the Popes ſupremacie, this is the ſumme of all, that they doe ſeeke their owne domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, the honour, the wealth, the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of this worlde: they will rather ſpoile Princes and Emperours all of their right, then any part of their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eminence or commodities ſhal be em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paired. Vppon this ground to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie their ambition, their coueteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, their luſtes, beſide dominions in Italie, which with Italian poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies by the diſcorde of kings and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours they haue gotten into their hands: they haue endeuored to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, as I haue ſhewed in Hildebrand and might at large in ſundrie others, which I omit for breueties ſake, they haue don I ſay whatſoeuer they could to take away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Emperours, Kings,
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:8222:60"/> noblemen, gentleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and all the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poralitie, as they did terme it, their liberties of patronages, donations &amp; preſentations of al ſpiritual promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, in al kingdomes and countries, reſeruing to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues either alone, or eſpecially full power, &amp; authoritie to giue biſhoprickes, and Abbayes, and Prebendes, &amp; perſonages, and other ſuch liuings. And al to maintain their inordinate ambition, their exceſſe of riot, their imperial pompe, their fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſenſualitie, which are the naturall children of the Romiſh ſupremacie, the daughter of coueteouſnes &amp; pride, the mother of miſchiefes and all abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <head>Chap. 14.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>Howe the Princes of England made many lawes and ſtatutes, againſt the Popiſh ſupremacie long before the time of King Henrie the eight, who did roote it out wholy.</p>
               </argument>
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:8222:61"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hus hauing; hitherto ſhewed &amp; declared, how the ſupremacy, and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacie of Rome, béeing not planted by Chriſte and his Apoſtles, was rooted firſt in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church by Boniface the third, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward ſpreade abroade farther and farther by his ſucceſſours, ſo that it grew and brought forth the poyſoned fruites, which I haue rehearſed: Now it doeth remaine, that I proceede to ſhew how it hath ben rooted out of the Church of England by godly princes of famous memorie: whoſe examples ſome princes haue, I wiſh all princes of the earth would follow. And herein I ſhall euidently diſcouer and refute their errour, who béeing counted men of good knowledge and iudgement, haue borne me in hand, that the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er &amp; authoritie of the Pope of Rome was neuer baniſhed out of this our countrie, vntill that King Henrie the eight did expell it, in the xxvj. yeare of his raigne, in the yeare of our Lord a thouſand fiue hundred thirtie &amp; foure.
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:8222:61"/> For it is certaine, and ſhal be clearely proued, that many yeares before that King Henrie the eight was borne, or King Henries Fathers Father, the kinges of this Realme haue made lawes and ſtatutes, againſt the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome his authoritie and iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction, whiche he did wrongfully clayme and vſurp within their domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, and therefore they did iuſtly remoue it and expell it. To the which purpoſe it muſt be firſte conſidered, that vnder the colour of the decrées a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue mentioned, the Popes did take vpon them to preferre ſtrangers vnto the roomes of Archbiſhops and biſhops throughout the Realme of England, many yeares together: and to place whom they liſt Abbots, and Priors in any religious houſes, when ſo euer that the places were voide: neither onely to preſent vnto all manner of religious houſes, but alſo to Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bends, Prouoſtries, Deanries, Parſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nages, and ſuch like. Which thinges as they were done to the great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peachment of the kings dignitie and
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:8222:62"/> crowne imperiall of the Realme: ſo did they tend alſo to the diſinheritance after a ſort, of his maieſtie, of his cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellours, of the nobilitie, of other his ſubiectes, which had by inheritaunce the giftes of ſuch liuings: and to the great loſſe of the whole countrie, by decay of hoſpitalitie, and conueying of our treaſures out of the Realme, through the meanes of ſtraungers, who were preferred to theſe liuinges and ſpirituall promotions. For re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe of which faultes, the nobles and commons of this Realme, at the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leament holden at Carlile in xxv.<note place="margin">Anno. Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni. 1296.</note> yere of the raigne of King Edward the firſt did preſent and exhibite a bill into the Parleament, of all the inconuenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and iniuries offered to the kinges maieſtie, the nobles, and commons by the Biſhop of Rome. Wherevpon the Parleament tooke order, and enacted, that from thence forth the Biſhop of Romes authoritie ſhold take no place within this Realme in any ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: if he dealt in any, they ſhould be voide and of none effect. Which act
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:8222:62"/> made againſte the Biſhop of Rome, becauſe there was no penaltie ſet vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch as did mainteine or ſuffer his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings to preuaile againſt the order ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken: therefore not long after the death of this good king Edward the firſt, Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the ſecond his ſonne, being king, a man of no ſuche courage as his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther was, neither hauing leaſure tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough his great troubles with the Earle Mortimer and the Quéene his wife to looke to ſuch matters, the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of Rome did ſpring againe to doe what he would. The ſubſtance of this Act, made by king Edward the firſt, is not recited in the ſtatutes of the xxv. yere of his raigne: becauſe it is wholy mentioned in the firſt part of the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute made the xxv. yere of King Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the third. At the which time, in a Parleament holden at Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, the ſame petition and Act made at Carlile was returned,<note place="margin">Anno Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni 1350. cap. 1.</note> and more ample order taken withal againſt the Biſhop of Rome. For it was prouided there and enacted, that whoſoeuer did fetche from Rome, or take any ſuch
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:8222:63"/> prouiſions to diſturbe any preſentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or election made in this Realme, or the perſons that were in poſſeſſion of any ſpirituall promotions: that the prouiſors and diſturbers, their procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators, executors, notaries, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tournies, ſhould be attached, and laid in priſon, without baile, or mainpriſe: there to remaine vntil both they had anſwered the king ſuch fine and raun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome as ſhold be taxed at his pleaſure: and alſo had agréed with the partie wronged: neither ſhould they be deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered vntill they had put in ſufficient ſureties neuer to attempt any ſuche thing afterward.<note place="margin">Cap. 1.</note> Againe in the xxvij. yeare of his raign in the Parleament holden at Weſtminſter, the ſame ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute was inlarged, and the penaltie made, that the offenders therein if they came not to anſwere at their day in proper perſon, and were found cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable, they ſhould forfaite all their landes, and goodes, their bodie ſhould remaine in priſon, &amp; out of the kinges protection. It appeareth farther in the xxx. yeare that an exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mengment,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:8222:63"/> as they do tearme it, was certified by the Pope: whiche was diſallowed by the Iuſtices, and the bringer thereof ſhould haue bene hanged and drawne, if the Chancelour of England had not prayed to the king for him. In the xxxviij. yeare, the like acte was made, for ſuch as procured any citations or proceſſes from the court of Rome: that their procurers and attourneyes ſhould haue ſuch puniſhmentes and forfaitures as are before mentioned. Now in the time of king Richard the ſecond, who did next ſuccéed him, there was a ſtatute made the thirtéenth yeare of his reigne,<note place="margin">Anno Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni. 1363. Cap. 1.</note> in the Parleament at Weſtminſter, againſte prouiſors of benefices, with this penaltie: that they ſhould be out of the kings protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and forfeit the benefice. But in the ſixtéenth yeare of his reigne,<note place="margin">Cap. 15.</note> the ſame king made more full and ſtraite lawes againſt the Biſhop of Rome: whereby he baniſhed his whole au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie out of this realme, enacting, that no proceſſe from Rome ſhould be allowed: Yea further,<note place="margin">Cap. 5.</note> that if any ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:8222:64"/> of this realme ſhould receiue, or fetch from Rome, or ſet forth any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner Citations, Preſentations, Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, Buls, or any other things againſt the kings regaltie &amp; crowne: he being conuict thereof, ſhould looſe and forfet all his landes and goods to the king, &amp; his body to be at the kinges pleaſure, and out of his protection, and in the cauſe of <hi>praemunire.</hi> The ſame puniſhment alſo appointed for him, who ſo euer ſhould ſue any appeale to Rome. King Henrie the fourth which ſuccéeded Richard, in the ſecond yeare of his reigne, in the parlament holden at Weſtminſter,<note place="margin">An. Do. 1401. Capit. 3.4.</note> did likewiſe make a lawe, that no ſpirituall or religious perſon, ſecular or regular, ſhould take any maner of promotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or liuing ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual, or offices in any ſpiritual hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, by any prouiſions of Licences or Buls fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Rome, vnder the payne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the <hi>praemunire,</hi> as in the firſt &amp; fourth Chapter of that ſtatute is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared. Againe in his ſixt yeare, at the parleament holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at Couentrie,<note place="margin">Capit. 1.</note> there was a lawe made to eaſe Archbiſhops
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:8222:64"/> and Biſhops of their great exactions, taken by the Pope and his officers of his chamber, for their firſt fruites. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in his ſeuenth yeare, an other lawe was made touching the Licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Pardons graunted from Rome to the incumbents of any bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, that whether they were graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, or to be graunted, they ſhould be vtterly voyde, and of none effect. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in his ninth yeare, bycauſe the Archbiſhoppes and Biſhoppes of this realme,<note place="margin">Capit. 8.</note> were after their elections greatly troubled by the Biſhoppe of Rome, it was enacted that the electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Archbiſhops, Biſhops, Abbats, Priors, and other ſpirituall perſons, ſhould be frée from all manner of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruptions and incumbrances of the Biſhop of Rome.<note place="margin">An. Do. 1407</note> It were tedious to goe forward in the like ſort with the Princes that followed: but by this taſte the wiſe may eaſily perceiue, howe no lawe could bridle the vnruly vſurpation of the Pope of Rome, but almoſt vnder the reigne of euery Prince, for the ſpace of two or thrée
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:8222:65"/> hundred yeares, they were compelled to renue olde, and make newe prouiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and actes of Parliament againſt him: Notwithſtanding all the which, his dealings were ſo outragious, and gathered eftſoones new ſtrength: that they could neuer be throughly repreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, vntill that God did raiſe vp our noble Prince of famous memorie King Henrie the eight, who percey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing and vnderſtanding, as well by his owne iudgement and knowledge, as alſo by the learned Cleargie of his realme, howe the Biſhops of Rome haue of long time fallen away from the ſound and pure religion of Chriſt, by their corrupt doctrine and abho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable pride: extolling them ſelues, not onely aboue all Biſhops, but alſo aboue all Emperours, Kings, and Princes of the earth: diſobeying the authoritie of rulers and magiſtrates, whom the Lord ſet ouer them, whom Chriſt did obey, whome the Apoſtles were ſubiect to: ſpeaking lyes thro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ugh hypocryſie, as they of whom S. Paul doeth prophecie,<note place="margin">1. Tim. 4.</note> forbidding to
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:8222:65"/> marrie, and commanding to abſtaine from meates, which God hath created to be receiued with giuing of thanks, of them who beléeue and knowe the truth: &amp; to come to the chiefeſt point, deuiſing blind, erronious, prophane &amp; vngodly meanes of obtaining ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by gadding in pilgrimage, by oblations to images, by kiſſing of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liques, by numbring of <hi>Pater noſters</hi> and <hi>Aue Maries</hi> vpon beades, by go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing barefoote and barelegged, by crée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping to croſſes, by their pardons <hi>a poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na &amp; culpa,</hi> with a number of péeuiſh toyes and ſuperſtitious ceremonies, to the blemiſhing of true faith, the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chorhold of all Chriſtians, grounded on aſſured hope of ſaluation, by the death &amp; paſſion of our ſauiour Chriſt, which is empaired by Poperie: the the Noble Prince therfore, King Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie the eight, ſéeing and conſidering theſe deteſtable enormities, and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked vſurpation of the Pope of Rome, did vtterly baniſh his counterfet au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority out of this realme of England, with the appurtenances of it. Which
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:8222:66"/> hauing him ſelfe begun in part to doe, he had it confirmed with the conſent of the whole realme, by ſtatute and lawe made in the eight and twentie yeare of his reigne, at a Parleament holden at Weſtminſter,<note place="margin">An. Do. 1536. Capit. 10.</note> to the great comfort of all his faithfull ſubiectes, to the reuiuing of the dignitie of his imperiall crowne, and moſt of all to the true honour and glory of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie. After this noble King, there ſuccéeded the godly worthie Prince his ſonne, King Edward the ſixt, who not onely confirmed that lawe againſt the Biſhop of Rome, but further pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>céeded in the eſtabliſhment of true religion. And of late againe (albeit) ſome interruption grewe in the time of Quéene Marie, Our moſt vertuous and gratious Souereigne, Quéene <hi>ELIZABETH,</hi> following the godly ſteps of her noble father and brother, had it inacted in her firſt parleament, that the authoritie of the Biſhoppe of Rome, and of al other forraine power, and potentates, ſpirituall and tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, ſhould vtterly be driuen away,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:8222:66"/> and remoued out of all her maieſties territories &amp; dominions: &amp; that vpon ſuch penalties vnto all her ſubiectes, that to vpholde, maintaine, or ſet forth any ſuch forraine authoritie w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in this realme, it is in ſome pointes and degrées high treaſon: ſo that they loſe and forfaite their liues, landes, &amp; goodes, who are guiltie of it. A ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute that may ſéeme ſeuere, and is perhappes accounted of ſome ouerri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous: but they who marke it wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cannot chooſe, but ſée howe ſharpe tooles were neceſſary to roote out this wéede, which many godly Princes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore King Henrie the eight did ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to nip of by ſundrie good lawes, but it budded ſtill againe, &amp; brought forth ſuch bloſſomes, or rather fruits, of rebellion, ambition, coueteouſnes, hipocriſie, &amp; wicked ſuperſtition, as it was to be feared woulde haue poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned the whole lande, had not our gratious prince vſed ſuch ſharpe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentes to roote it out vtterly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:8222:67"/>
               <head>Chap. 15.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>A ſhort repetition of the pointes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, witha co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſion of the whole. And an exhortation to the people of Englande to embrace this truth, with all the heauenly doctrine of Chriſtes religion.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Herefore I doe wiſhe euen from the very bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of my hearte, that euerie faithfull ſubiect, and right Chriſtian ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> woulde weigh both this point, &amp; al the reſt, which I haue ſaide, to ſatiſfie his conſcience in this matter of the ſupre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macie: leaſt they builde vppon ſande, not on the rocke, Ieſus Chriſt. Let vs conſider y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our ſauiour did not graunt it to any of his Apoſtles: nay he did ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely forbidde ſuch ouerruling and dominion amongeſt them. Let vs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that as it was not giuen by him to Saint Peter: ſo neyther did Saint Peter practiſe it, nor the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles attribute it vnto him. Though it had beene giuen to Peter amongeſt
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:8222:67"/> the reſt: yet what reaſon is it that the Biſhoppe of Rome ſhould be his heire in it? ſyth we reade not in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures that Peter euer was at Rome: which we ſhould haue redd doubtles, if it had ben of ſo great weight. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto we muſt adde, that in the primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue Church this preemine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce was not acknowleged, either to, or by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoppes of Rome. The godly Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes of that Citie, who many of them were martyres, did not take it vppon them. The fower firſt principall and generall councels aſſembled out of all Chriſtendome, did not yeelde it vnto them. What haue we then to do with Boniface the thirde, to whome the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of ſupremacie was graunted firſte by wicked Phocas? What haue wee to doe with Boniface his ſucceſſors: who haue ſat in the chaire of peſtilenc and haue made their ſcepter a ſcepter of iniquitie? ſhall wee rather followe them, then Chriſt, then Peter, then y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Apoſtles, then generall councels, then godly Biſhoppes of Rome? Shall we not be wiſe, and learne to make a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:8222:68"/> betwéene the firſt Byſhoppes that were in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Citie, frée fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition: and betwéene the later, who ſwarued fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their ſtepes? For as they did followe Chriſte and his Apoſtles in preachinge and teaching the holy word of God, in miniſtring the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes in plaine and humble ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner: in ordering well the flocke of Chriſte by good and wholeſome diſcipline: ſo theſe of the other ſide, after that they had obteined y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſupremacy of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, they encreaſed the ſéedes of er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and ſuperſtition, which before were caſt, and fell away more &amp; more from Chriſts example &amp; doctrine, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king them ſelues a newe prieſthoode, &amp; framing it after the manner of the prieſthoode amongeſt the Iewes, both by chaunging the miniſtration of the Lordes ſupper into a ſacrifice propitiatorie, and an oblation for the ſinnes of the liuing and of the deade, though they were not partakers of it: and alſo by deuiſing to themſelues ſuch gaye and diſguiſed veſtures of cloth of golde and ſiluer, of veluet &amp;
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:8222:68"/> ſuch other ſtuffe, ſo that not Aaron was apparailed more gorgeouſly the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they. But this was the leaſt faulte: yet out of doubt a fault. For our ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt did not abrogate the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies of the lawe of Moſes, to bring in others like vnto them. But other thinges were greater, and moſt of all to be condemned in theſe By<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopps of the ſupremacie: y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they deui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed new wayes and meanes for me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to obtaine forgiuenes of their ſinnes and euerlaſting life, ſuch as neither Chriſt our ſauiour did ordeine, neither did they aduaunce the glory of Chriſt, our onely ſauiour. For they deuiſed that men might bee ſaued by their owne workes, and by praying to images, and by going a pilgrimage, and by ſetting vp of candles before the pic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of ſaintes, and by purchaſing of Pardons from the Biſhop of Rome, ſpecially, if they were pardons called a <hi>Poena &amp; culpa,</hi> and by trentals, and diriges, and by Maſſes of <hi>Requiem,</hi> &amp; of <hi>Scala coeli,</hi> and by their tapers of waxe, and by their ſacring belles, and
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:8222:69"/> clackes, and by their paſcall, and by their pax, by their ſenſinges and ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnities, by their deuout créeping to croſſes and wearing of cowles of Moonkes, and ſuch other a thouſande trumperies, holy creame, holy oyle, holy bowes, holy aſhes, holy breade, holy water, to keepe them from euill ſpirites, and I know not what. Thus they ledde the people from their faith, and truſt in the bloode and death of our ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt, to put their faith and truſt in the Popes indulge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces, and in ſuch other blinde illuſions: to the great daunger of their ſoules, &amp; the diſhonour of the Lorde. Neither contented with this corruption of doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine, they brought in a greater co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of diſcipline: calling away the elections of Biſhoppes, and handling of Church matters, vnto the courte of Rome: where the Market was, for ſpirituall promotions, for deciding of controuerſies, for bying out of ſins, for keeping of concubines, for clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of purgatorie, for engroſing of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings, for non reſidence vpon them, &amp;
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:8222:69"/> for what not? All was at Rome, and might be had from Rome for money. The Lordes vineyeard did lie waſte. The Church was become a denne of theeues. Wherefore, good Chriſtian brethren and countrimen, ſyth the light of the Goſpell hath opened theſe thinges vnto vs: let no man deceiue vs vnder colour of antiquitie, or by ſaying, thus and thus our forefathers haue thought many hundred yeares paſt, and therefore it is good. For if you wil haue reſpect to antiquitie: the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doe, I beſeech you, as I haue here done: beginne at our ſauiour Chriſts time, and ſo come downe to ours, as it were by ſteppes, and you ſhall ſée that there is as great differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce betwixt the primitiue Church of Chriſt for fiue or ſixe hundred yeares, and theſe latter times of darkenes which followed y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> light, as is almoſt betwixt white and black in colour, or God and the deuill in goodneſſe. For the Biſhoppes of Rome in theſe latter ages haue ben ſo cleane contrarie in all reſpectes to Chriſt, that the Prophecie of ſaint
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:8222:70"/> Paul to the Theſſalonia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s doth ſéeme to be fulfilled in them:<note place="margin">2. Theſſ. 2.</note> in that he doth ſay, <hi>there ſhould be a departing firſt from the faith, and then the man of ſinne ſhoulde be diſcloſed, euen the child of perdition, which is an aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie to God, and exalteth him ſelfe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt higheſt.</hi> Which words, what Antichriſt can they deſcribe more liuely, then the Pope of Rome? For to paſſeouer his falling from the faith, and his corruption of doctrine which I haue already noted, as Chriſt was moſte humble and méeke: ſo the Popes are moſte hautie and proude. As Chriſt was moſt ſimple and poore: ſo the Popes are moſte ſubtil and ful of treaſures.<note place="margin">Iohn. 18.</note> As Chriſte ſaide his kingdom was not of this world: ſo the Popes doe lift them ſelues aboue the Princes of this worlde. As Chriſte went lowly vpon the ground: ſo the Popes muſt be carried aloft on mens ſhoulders for feare of touching the ground. As Chriſte in apparell, beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, and conuerſation, applyed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to common men: ſo the Popes in
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:8222:70"/> theſe thinges doe reſemble rather the maieſtie of Emperours. They may be wel compared to the Phariſées whom Chriſte did liken to painted tumbes,<note place="margin">Matt. 23.</note> which appeare beautiful in the vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, but are within, ful of dead mens bones and all filthineſſe. Such are the Biſhops of Rome, moſt rich in robes of cloth of Golde, their very ſhooes ſet with pretious ſtones: but within, their ſoules moſte filthie, with riot, couetouſneſſe, ambition, and other worldly vices, as their liues do ſhew, which are ſet forth vnto the world by Platina and others, men that knewe them well, and were conuerſant a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout them. Wherefore, ſith it is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt that vnder colour of holines pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending to be Chriſtes Vicars, they are Chriſtes aduerſaries, euen his greateſt aduerſaries, with drawing his people from their ſpeciall truſt in him to their own errours and wicked ſuperſtitions: therefore nowe, good Chriſtian brethren, let vs followe the counſel of the Scriptures.<note place="margin">Iohn. 12.</note> 
                  <hi>Dum lucem habemus, ambulemus in ea: <hi>While we haue the light, let vs walk in the light,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:8222:71"/> euen in the light of the Prophetes and Apoſtles.</hi>
                  </hi> Whereby Chriſt doth teach vs the falſehode of Antichriſt, that we may flye from him, and from all his workes of darkeneſſe: that we may deteſt his vniuſt ſupremacie, and er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ronious doctrine, and fantaſticall ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies, and all the dregges of Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylon.<note place="margin">Matt. 11.</note> 
                  <hi>Venite ad me omnes qui laboratis &amp; onerati eſtis, &amp; ego reficiam vos,</hi> ſaith our Sauiour Chriſt. <hi>Come vnto me all ye that are wearie and laden, and I will refreſhe you.</hi> I will refreſhe you, ſaith our Sauiour: he calleth moſte comfortably vnto him ſelfe, all, which are trouble and afflicted in mind, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the conſideration of the grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſneſſe of their ſinnes, whiche de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue eternall death, and are ready to caſt them into deſperation: and he do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth promiſe them, that hee will eaſe them, without ſuing to Rome for par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons, or hauing Maſſes, or trentals, or diriges, or other ſuch fooliſh fanſies of men. But he willeth them to come vnto himſelfe,<note place="margin">Matt. 1.</note> who was called Ieſus, that is to ſay, a Sauiour, by the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:8222:71"/> of God, becauſe that he ſhould ſaue his people from their ſins: of whom ſaint Iohn doth ſay,<note place="margin">1. Iohn. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Si quis peccauerit: aduocatum habemus apud pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem, Ieſum Chriſtum iuſtum: &amp; ipſe eſt propitiatio pro peccatis noſtris: non pro no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stris autem tantùm, ſed etiam pro totius mundi. <hi>If any man, ſinne,</hi>
                  </hi> ſaith Iohn the Euangeliſt, <hi>we haue an aduocate or Mediatour with God the Father, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt the iuſt: and he is the propi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, the pacifier of God, obteining mercy for our ſins, yet not for ours on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, but alſo for the ſinnes of the whole world.</hi> Wherefore ſith the Pope doth teach vs to haue other mediatours &amp; aduocates to the Father, euen the ſaints, whom himſelfe and his Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals haue canonized, and doth leade men ſo many wayes, as though they might be ſaued by them, where as our Sauiour Chriſt is the onely way,<note place="margin">Iohn. 8.</note> the trueth and the life: let vs leaue this falſe prieſt, and his buls, and his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dons, and the reſt of his trumperies, and let vs thinke well of our godly princes, who haue cut out the rootes
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:8222:72"/> of his ſupremacie, whence all the poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon doth flowe. For the ſtaying of the whiche, leaſt it ſhoulde bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyued into the bowels of the Realm, and corrupte the whole bodie: ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye godly Princes heretofore be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne that worke, by making ſundry lawes and ſtatutes, which in our dayes King Henrie the eight, King Edward the ſixt, and our gratious Quéene Elizabeth haue brought to good end, through the great mercy of God. That which our Sauiour ſaide, is fulfilled herein:<note place="margin">Math. 15.</note> 
                  <hi>Omnis plantatio quam pater meus coelestis non plantauit, eradicabitur: <hi>Euery plant which is not planted by my heauenly father, ſhall be pulled vp by the roote.</hi>
                  </hi> The light of Chriſtes Goſpell hath openly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloſed to vs that man of ſinne, and childe of perdition, which taketh on him to ſit in the temple of GOD, as God. It is manifeſt that his ſuprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, with all his errours builded on it, are plantes which were not planted by God our heauenly father. God wil therefore roote them out, according to
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:8222:72"/> his promiſe: vpon the which promiſe, in part fulfilled already, we are to make our daily prayers, that he will more and more fulfill it: that he will roote out all, ſpéedily, and throughly, not onely out of our Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, but out of all peoples conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: that the ſeruants of God may be ioyned altogether in one Chriſtian faith, ſetting their whole confidence in Ieſus Chriſte alone, the ſonne of the liuing GOD, who ſuffered cruell death, and ſhed his pretious bloud for the raunſome of all our ſinnes, as many as beléeue in him, that he might ioyne vs to him ſelfe, and preſent vs to his father, making vs partakers of his owne glory with him. Which the Lord graunt vs of his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite mercy, through our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatour and ſauiour Ieſus Chriſt. Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:8222:73"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8222:73"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
